Chapter 1. Asynchrony: Now & Later

One of the most important and yet often misunderstood parts of programming in a language like JavaScript is how to express and manipulate program behavior spread out over a period of time.

This is not just about what happens from the beginning of a for loop to the end of a for loop, which of course takes some time (microseconds to milliseconds) to complete. It’s about what happens when part of your program runs now, and another part of your program runs later—there’s a gap between now and later where your program isn’t actively executing.

Practically all nontrivial programs ever written (especially in JS) have in some way or another had to manage this gap, whether that be in waiting for user input, requesting data from a database or file system, sending data across the network and waiting for a response, or performing a repeated task at a fixed interval of time (like animation). In all these various ways, your program has to manage state across the gap in time. As they famously say in London (of the chasm between the subway door and the platform): “mind the gap.”

In fact, the relationship between the now and later parts of your program is at the heart of asynchronous programming.

Asynchronous programming has been around since the beginning of JS, for sure. But most JS developers have never really carefully considered exactly how and why it crops up in their programs, or explored various other ways to handle it. The good enough approach has always been the humble callback function. Many to this day will insist that callbacks are more than sufficient.

But as JS continues to grow in both scope and complexity, to meet the ever-widening demands of a first-class programming language that runs in browsers and servers and every conceivable device in between, the pains by which we manage asynchrony are becoming increasingly crippling, and they cry out for approaches that are both more capable and more reason-able.

While this all may seem rather abstract right now, I assure you we’ll tackle it more completely and concretely as we go on through this book. We’ll explore a variety of emerging techniques for async JavaScript programming over the next several chapters.

But before we can get there, we’re going to have to understand much more deeply what asynchrony is and how it operates in JS.

A Program in Chunks

You may write your JS program in one .js file, but your program is almost certainly comprised of several chunks, only one of which is going to execute now, and the rest of which will execute later. The most common unit of each chunk is the function.

The problem most developers new to JS seem to have is that later doesn’t happen strictly and immediately after now. In other words, tasks that cannot complete now are, by definition, going to complete asynchronously, and thus we will not have blocking behavior as you might intuitively expect or want.

Consider:

// ajax(..) is some arbitrary Ajax function given by a library
var data = ajax( "http://some.url.1" );

console.log( data );
// Oops! `data` generally won't have the Ajax results

You’re probably aware that standard Ajax requests don’t complete synchronously, which means the ajax(..) function does not yet have any value to return back to be assigned to the data variable. If ajax(..) could block until the response came back, then the data = .. assignment would work fine.

But that’s not how we do Ajax. We make an asynchronous Ajax request now, and we won’t get the results back until later.

The simplest (but definitely not only, or necessarily even best!) way of “waiting” from now until later is to use a function, commonly called a callback function:

// ajax(..) is some arbitrary Ajax function given by a library
ajax( "http://some.url.1", function myCallbackFunction(data){

    console.log( data ); // Yay, I gots me some `data`!

} );

Warning

You may have heard that it’s possible to make synchronous Ajax requests. While that’s technically true, you should never, ever do it, under any circumstances, because it locks the browser UI (buttons, menus, scrolling, etc.) and prevents any user interaction whatsoever. This is a terrible idea, and should always be avoided.

Before you protest in disagreement, no, your desire to avoid the mess of callbacks is not justification for blocking, synchronous Ajax.

For example, consider this code:

function now() {
    return 21;
}

function later() {
    answer = answer * 2;
    console.log( "Meaning of life:", answer );
}

var answer = now();

setTimeout( later, 1000 ); // Meaning of life: 42

There are two chunks to this program: the stuff that will run now, and the stuff that will run later. It should be fairly obvious what those two chunks are, but let’s be super explicit:

Now:

function now() {
    return 21;
}

function later() { .. }

var answer = now();

setTimeout( later, 1000 );

Later:

answer = answer * 2;
console.log( "Meaning of life:", answer );

The now chunk runs right away, as soon as you execute your program. But setTimeout(..) also sets up an event (a timeout) to happen later, so the contents of the later() function will be executed at a later time (1,000 milliseconds from now).

Any time you wrap a portion of code into a function and specify that it should be executed in response to some event (timer, mouse click, Ajax response, etc.), you are creating a later chunk of your code, and thus introducing asynchrony to your program.

Async Console

There is no specification or set of requirements around how the console.* methods work—they are not officially part of JavaScript, but are instead added to JS by the hosting environment (see the Types & Grammar title of this series).

So, different browsers and JS environments do as they please, which can sometimes lead to confusing behavior.

In particular, there are some browsers and some conditions that console.log(..) does not actually immediately output what it’s given. The main reason this may happen is because I/O is a very slow and blocking part of many programs (not just JS). So, it may perform better (from the page/UI perspective) for a browser to handle console I/O asynchronously in the background, without you perhaps even knowing that occurred.

A not terribly common, but possible, scenario where this could be observable (not from code itself but from the outside):

var a = {
    index: 1
};

// later
console.log( a ); // ??

// even later
a.index++;

We’d normally expect to see the a object be snapshotted at the exact moment of the console.log(..) statement, printing something like { index: 1 }, such that in the next statement when a.index++ happens, it’s modifying something different than, or just strictly after, the output of a.

Most of the time, the preceding code will probably produce an object representation in your developer tools’ console that’s what you’d expect. But it’s possible this same code could run in a situation where the browser felt it needed to defer the console I/O to the background, in which case it’s possible that by the time the object is represented in the browser console, the a.index++ has already happened, and it shows { index: 2 }.

It’s a moving target under what conditions exactly console I/O will be deferred, or even whether it will be observable. Just be aware of this possible asynchronicity in I/O in case you ever run into issues in debugging where objects have been modified after a console.log(..) statement and yet you see the unexpected modifications show up.

Note

If you run into this rare scenario, the best option is to use breakpoints in your JS debugger instead of relying on console output. The next best option would be to force a “snapshot” of the object in question by serializing it to a string, like with JSON.stringify(..).

Event Loop

Let’s make a (perhaps shocking) claim: despite your clearly being able to write asynchronous JS code (like the timeout we just looked at), up until recently (ES6), JavaScript itself has actually never had any direct notion of asynchrony built into it.

What!? That seems like a crazy claim, right? In fact, it’s quite true. The JS engine itself has never done anything more than execute a single chunk of your program at any given moment, when asked to.

“Asked to.” By whom? That’s the important part!

The JS engine doesn’t run in isolation. It runs inside a hosting environment, which is for most developers the typical web browser. Over the last several years (but by no means exclusively), JS has expanded beyond the browser into other environments, such as servers, via things like Node.js. In fact, JavaScript gets embedded into all kinds of devices these days, from robots to lightbulbs.

But the one common “thread” (that’s a not-so-subtle asynchronous joke, for what it’s worth) of all these environments is that they have a mechanism in them that handles executing multiple chunks of your program over time, at each moment invoking the JS engine, called the event loop.

In other words, the JS engine has had no innate sense of time, but has instead been an on-demand execution environment for any arbitrary snippet of JS. It’s the surrounding environment that has always scheduled “events” (JS code executions).

So, for example, when your JS program makes an Ajax request to fetch some data from a server, you set up the response code in a function (commonly called a callback), and the JS engine tells the hosting environment, “Hey, I’m going to suspend execution for now, but whenever you finish with that network request, and you have some data, please call this function back.”

The browser is then set up to listen for the response from the network, and when it has something to give you, it schedules the callback function to be executed by inserting it into the event loop.

So what is the event loop?

Let’s conceptualize it first through some fake-ish code:

// `eventLoop` is an array that acts as a queue
// (first-in, first-out)
var eventLoop = [ ];
var event;

// keep going "forever"
while (true) {
    // perform a "tick"
    if (eventLoop.length > 0) {
        // get the next event in the queue
        event = eventLoop.shift();

        // now, execute the next event
        try {
            event();
        }
        catch (err) {
            reportError(err);
        }
    }
}

This is, of course, vastly simplified pseudocode to illustrate the concepts. But it should be enough to help get a better understanding.

As you can see, there’s a continuously running loop represented by the while loop, and each iteration of this loop is called a tick. For each tick, if an event is waiting on the queue, it’s taken off and executed. These events are your function callbacks.

It’s important to note that setTimeout(..) doesn’t put your callback on the event loop queue. What it does is set up a timer; when the timer expires, the environment places your callback into the event loop, such that some future tick will pick it up and execute it.

What if there are already 20 items in the event loop at that moment? Your callback waits. It gets in line behind the others—there’s not normally a path for preempting the queue and skipping ahead in line. This explains why setTimeout(..) timers may not fire with perfect temporal accuracy. You’re guaranteed (roughly speaking) that your callback won’t fire before the time interval you specify, but it can happen at or after that time, depending on the state of the event queue.

So, in other words, your program is generally broken up into lots of small chunks, which happen one after the other in the event loop queue. And technically, other events not related directly to your program can be interleaved within the queue as well.

Note

We mentioned “up until recently” in relation to ES6 changing the nature of where the event loop queue is managed. It’s mostly a formal technicality, but ES6 now specifies exactly how the event loop works, which means technically it’s within the purview of the JS engine, rather than just the hosting environment. One main reason for this change is the introduction of ES6 Promises, which we’ll discuss in Chapter 3, because they require the ability to have direct, fine-grained control over scheduling operations on the event loop queue (see the discussion of setTimeout(..0) in “Cooperation”).

Concurrency

Let’s imagine a site that displays a list of status updates (like a social network news feed) that progressively loads as the user scrolls down the list. To make such a feature work correctly, (at least) two separate “processes” will need to be executing simultaneously (i.e., during the same window of time, but not necessarily at the same instant).

Note

We’re using “process” in quotes here because they aren’t true operating system–level processes in the computer science sense. They’re virtual processes, or tasks, that represent a logically connected, sequential series of operations. We’ll use “process” instead of “task” because terminology-wise, it matches the definitions of the concepts we’re exploring.

The first “process” will respond to onscroll events (making Ajax requests for new content) as they fire when the user has scrolled the page further down. The second “process” will receive Ajax responses back (to render content onto the page).

Obviously, if a user scrolls fast enough, you may see two or more onscroll events fired during the time it takes to get the first response back and process, and thus you’re going to have onscroll events and Ajax response events firing rapidly, interleaved with each other.

Concurrency is when two or more “processes” are executing simultaneously over the same period, regardless of whether their individual constituent operations happen in parallel (at the same instant on separate processors or cores). You can think of concurrency then as “process”-level (or task-level) parallelism, as opposed to operation-level parallelism (separate-processor threads).

Note

Concurrency also introduces an optional notion of these “processes” interacting with each other. We’ll come back to that later.

For a given window of time (a few seconds worth of a user scrolling), let’s visualize each independent “process” as a series of events/operations:

“Process” 1 (onscroll events):

onscroll, request 1
onscroll, request 2
onscroll, request 3
onscroll, request 4
onscroll, request 5
onscroll, request 6
onscroll, request 7

“Process” 2 (Ajax response events):

response 1
response 2
response 3
response 4
response 5
response 6
response 7

It’s quite possible that an onscroll event and an Ajax response event could be ready to be processed at exactly the same moment. For example, let’s visualize these events in a timeline:

onscroll, request 1
onscroll, request 2          response 1
onscroll, request 3          response 2
response 3
onscroll, request 4
onscroll, request 5
onscroll, request 6          response 4
onscroll, request 7
response 6
response 5
response 7

But, going back to our notion of the event loop from earlier in the chapter, JS can handle only one event at a time, so either onscroll, request 2 is going to happen first or response 1 is going to happen first, but they cannot happen at literally the same moment. Just like kids at a school cafeteria, no matter what crowd they form outside the doors, they’ll have to merge into a single line to get their lunch!

Let’s visualize the interleaving of all these events onto the event loop queue:

onscroll, request 1   <--- Process 1 starts
onscroll, request 2
response 1            <--- Process 2 starts
onscroll, request 3
response 2
response 3
onscroll, request 4
onscroll, request 5
onscroll, request 6
response 4
onscroll, request 7   <--- Process 1 finishes
response 6
response 5
response 7            <--- Process 2 finishes

“Process” 1 and “Process” 2 run concurrently (task-level parallel), but their individual events run sequentially on the event loop queue.

By the way, notice how response 6 and response 5 came back out of expected order?

The single-threaded event loop is one expression of concurrency (there are certainly others, which we’ll come back to later).

Jobs

As of ES6, there’s a new concept layered on top of the event loop queue, called the Job queue. The most likely exposure you’ll have to it is with the asynchronous behavior of Promises (see Chapter 3).

Unfortunately, at the moment it’s a mechanism without an exposed API, and thus demonstrating it is a bit more convoluted. So we’re going to describe it conceptually, such that when we discuss async behavior with Promises in Chapter 3, you’ll understand how those actions are being scheduled and processed.

So, the best way to think about this that I’ve found is that the Job queue is a queue hanging off the end of every tick in the event loop queue. Certain async-implied actions that may occur during a tick of the event loop will not cause a whole new event to be added to the event loop queue, but will instead add an item (aka Job) to the end of the current tick’s Job queue.

It’s kinda like saying, “oh, here’s this other thing I need to do later, but make sure it happens right away before anything else can happen.”

The event loop queue is like an amusement park ride: once you finish the ride, you have to go to the back of the line to ride again. But the Job queue is like finishing the ride, cutting in line, and getting right back on.

A Job can also cause more Jobs to be added to the end of the same queue. So, it’s theoretically possible that a Job loop (a Job that keeps adding another Job, etc.) could spin indefinitely, thus starving the program of the ability to move on to the next event loop tick. This would conceptually be almost the same as just expressing a long-running or infinite loop (like while (true) ..) in your code.

Jobs are kind of like the spirit of the setTimeout(..0) hack, but implemented in such a way as to have a much more well-defined and guaranteed ordering: later, but as soon as possible.

Let’s imagine an API for scheduling Jobs (directly, without hacks), and call it schedule(..). Consider:

console.log( "A" );

setTimeout( function(){
    console.log( "B" );
}, 0 );

// theoretical "Job API"
schedule( function(){
    console.log( "C" );

    schedule( function(){
        console.log( "D" );
    } );
} );

You might expect this to print out A B C D, but instead it would print out A C D B, because the Jobs happen at the end of the current event loop tick, and the timer fires to schedule for the next event loop tick (if available!).

In Chapter 3, we’ll see that the asynchronous behavior of Promises is based on Jobs, so it’s important to keep clear how that relates to event loop behavior.

Review

A JavaScript program is (practically) always broken up into two or more chunks, where the first chunk runs now and the next chunk runs later, in response to an event. Even though the program is executed chunk-by-chunk, all of them share the same access to the program scope and state, so each modification to state is made on top of the previous state.

Whenever there are events to run, the event loop runs until the queue is empty. Each iteration of the event loop is a tick. User interaction, IO, and timers enqueue events on the event queue.

At any given moment, only one event can be processed from the queue at a time. While an event is executing, it can directly or indirectly cause one or more subsequent events.

Concurrency is when two or more chains of events interleave over time, such that from a high-level perspective, they appear to be running simultaneously (even though at any given moment only one event is being processed).

It’s often necessary to do some form of interaction coordination between these concurrent “processes” (as distinct from operating system processes), for instance to ensure ordering or to prevent race conditions. These “processes” can also cooperate by breaking themselves into smaller chunks and to allow other “process” interleaving.

Chapter 2. Callbacks

In Chapter 1, we explored the terminology and concepts around asynchronous programming in JavaScript. Our focus is on understanding the single-threaded (one-at-a-time) event loop queue that drives all events (async function invocations). We also explored various ways that concurrency patterns explain the relationships (if any!) between simultaneously running chains of events, or “processes” (tasks, function calls, etc.).

All our examples in Chapter 1 used the function as the individual, indivisible unit of operations, whereby inside the function, statements run in predictable order (above the compiler level!), but at the function-ordering level, events (aka async function invocations) can happen in a variety of orders.

In all these cases, the function is acting as a callback, because it serves as the target for the event loop to “call back into” the program, whenever that item in the queue is processed.

As you no doubt have observed, callbacks are by far the most common way that asynchrony in JS programs is expressed and managed. Indeed, the callback is the most fundamental async pattern in the language.

Countless JS programs, even very sophisticated and complex ones, have been written upon no other async foundation than the callback (with, of course, the concurrency interaction patterns we explored in Chapter 1). The callback function is the async workhorse for JavaScript, and it does its job respectably.

Except…callbacks are not without their shortcomings. Many developers are excited by the promise (pun intended!) of better async patterns. But it’s impossible to effectively use any abstraction if you don’t understand what it’s abstracting, and why.

In this chapter, we will explore a couple of those in depth, as motivation for why more sophisticated async patterns (explored in subsequent chapters of this book and Appendix B) are necessary and desired.

Continuations

Let’s go back to the async callback example we started with in Chapter 1, but let me slightly modify it to illustrate a point:

// A
ajax( "..", function(..){
    // C
} );
// B

// A and // B represent the first half of the program (aka the now), and // C marks the second half of the program (aka the later). The first half executes right away, and then there’s a pause of indeterminate length. At some future moment, if the Ajax call completes, then the program will pick up where it left off, and continue with the second half.

In other words, the callback function wraps or encapsulates the continuation of the program.

Let’s make the code even simpler:

// A
setTimeout( function(){
    // C
}, 1000 );
// B

Stop for a moment and ask yourself how you’d describe (to someone else less informed about how JS works) the way that program behaves. Go ahead, try it out loud. It’s a good exercise that will help my next points make more sense.

Most readers just now probably thought or said something to the effect of: “Do A, then set up a timeout to wait 1,000 milliseconds, then once that fires, do C.” How close was your rendition?

You might have caught yourself and self-edited to: “Do A, set up the timeout for 1,000 milliseconds, then do B, then after the timeout fires, do C.” That’s more accurate than the first version. Can you spot the difference?

Even though the second version is more accurate, both versions are deficient in explaining this code in a way that matches our brains to the code, and the code to the JS engine. The disconnect is both subtle and monumental, and is at the very heart of understanding the shortcomings of callbacks as async expression and management.

As soon as we introduce a single continuation (or several dozen, as many programs do!) in the form of a callback function, we have allowed a divergence to form between how our brains work and the way the code will operate. Any time these two diverge (and this is by far not the only place that happens, as I’m sure you know!), we run into the inevitable fact that our code becomes harder to understand, reason about, debug, and maintain.

Sequential Brain

I’m pretty sure most of you have heard someone say, or made the claim yourself: “I’m a multitasker.” The effects of trying to act as a multitasker range from humorous (e.g., the silly patting-head-rubbing-stomach kids’ game) to mundane (chewing gum while walking) to downright dangerous (texting while driving).

But are we multitaskers? Can we really do two conscious, intentional actions at once and think/reason about both of them at exactly the same moment? Does our highest level of brain functionality have parallel multithreading going on?

The answer may surprise you: probably not.

That’s just not really how our brains appear to be set up. We’re much more single taskers than many of us (especially A-type personalities!) would like to admit. We can really only think about one thing at any given instant.

I’m not talking about all our involuntary, subconscious, automatic brain functions, such as heart beating, breathing, and eyelid blinking. Those are all vital tasks to our sustained life, but we don’t intentionally allocate any brain power to them. Thankfully, while we obsess about checking social network feeds for the 15th time in three minutes, our brain carries on in the background (threads!) with all those important tasks.

We’re instead talking about whatever task is at the forefront of our minds at the moment. For me, it’s writing the text in this book right now. Am I doing any other higher level brain function at exactly this same moment? Nope, not really. I get distracted quickly and easily—a few dozen times in these last couple of paragraphs!

When we fake multitasking, such as trying to type something at the same time we’re talking to a friend or family member on the phone, what we’re actually most likely doing is acting as fast context switchers. In other words, we switch back and forth between two or more tasks in rapid succession, simultaneously progressing on each task in tiny, fast little chunks. We do it so fast that to the outside world it appears as if we’re doing these things in parallel.

Does that sound suspiciously like async evented concurrency (like the sort that happens in JS) to you?! If not, go back and read Chapter 1 again!

In fact, one way of simplifying (i.e., abusing) the massively complex world of neurology into something I can remotely hope to discuss here is that our brains work kinda like the event loop queue.

If you think about every single letter (or word) I type as a single async event, in just this sentence alone there are several dozen opportunities for my brain to be interrupted by some other event, such as from my senses, or even just my random thoughts.

I don’t get interrupted and pulled to another “process” at every opportunity that I could be (thankfully—or this book would never be written!). But it happens often enough that I feel my own brain is nearly constantly switching to various different contexts (aka “processes”). And that’s an awful lot like how the JS engine would probably feel.

Doing Versus Planning

OK, so our brains can be thought of as operating in single-threaded event loop queue like ways, as can the JS engine. That sounds like a good match.

But we need to be more nuanced than that in our analysis. There’s a big, observable difference between how we plan various tasks, and how our brains actually perform those tasks.

Again, back to the writing of this text as my metaphor. My rough mental outline plan here is to keep writing and writing, going sequentially through a set of points I have ordered in my thoughts. I don’t plan to have any interruptions or nonlinear activity in this writing. But yet, my brain is nevertheless switching around all the time.

Even though at an operational level our brains are async evented, we seem to plan out tasks in a sequential, synchronous way. “I need to go to the store, then buy some milk, then drop off my dry cleaning.”

You’ll notice that this higher level thinking (planning) doesn’t seem very async evented in its formulation. In fact, it’s kind of rare for us to deliberately think solely in terms of events. Instead, we plan things out carefully, sequentially (A, then B, then C), and we assume to an extent a sort of temporal blocking that forces B to wait on A, and C to wait on B.

When a developer writes code, they are planning out a set of actions to occur. If they’re any good at being a developer, they’re carefully planning it out. “I need to set z to the value of x, and then x to the value of y,” and so forth.

When we write out synchronous code, statement by statement, it works a lot like our errands to-do list:

// swap `x` and `y` (via temp variable `z`)
z = x;
x = y;
y = z;

These three assignment statements are synchronous, so x = y waits for z = x to finish, and y = z in turn waits for x = y to finish. Another way of saying it is that these three statements are temporally bound to execute in a certain order, one right after the other. Thankfully, we don’t need to be bothered with any async evented details here. If we did, the code gets a lot more complex, quickly!

So if synchronous brain planning maps well to synchronous code statements, how well do our brains do at planning out asynchronous code?

It turns out that how we express asynchrony (with callbacks) in our code doesn’t map very well at all to that synchronous brain planning behavior.

Can you actually imagine having a line of thinking that plans out your to-do errands like this?

“I need to go to the store, but on the way I’m sure I’ll get a phone call, so Hi, Mom, and while she starts talking, I’ll be looking up the store address on GPS, but that’ll take a second to load, so I’ll turn down the radio so I can hear Mom better, then I’ll realize I forgot to put on a jacket and it’s cold outside, but no matter, keep driving and talking to Mom, and then the seatbelt ding reminds me to buckle up, so yes, Mom, I am wearing my seatbelt, I always do! Ah, finally the GPS got the directions, now…”

As ridiculous as that sounds as a formulation for how we plan our day out and think about what to do and in what order, nonetheless it’s exactly how our brains operate at a functional level. Remember, that’s not multitasking, it’s just fast context switching.

The reason it’s difficult for us as developers to write async evented code, especially when all we have is the callback to do it, is that stream of consciousness thinking/planning is unnatural for most of us.

We think in step-by-step terms, but the tools (callbacks) available to us in code are not expressed in a step-by-step fashion once we move from synchronous to asynchronous.

And that is why it’s so hard to accurately author and reason about async JS code with callbacks: because it’s not how our brain planning works.

Note

The only thing worse than not knowing why some code breaks is not knowing why it worked in the first place! It’s the classic “house of cards” mentality: “it works, but I’m not sure why, so nobody touch it!” You may have heard, “Hell is other people” (Sartre), and the programmer meme twist, “Hell is other people’s code.” I believe truly: “Hell is not understanding my own code.” And callbacks are one main culprit.

Nested/Chained Callbacks

Consider:

listen( "click", function handler(evt){
    setTimeout( function request(){
        ajax( "http://some.url.1", function response(text){
            if (text == "hello") {
                handler();
            }
            else if (text == "world") {
                request();
            }
        } );
    }, 500) ;
} );

There’s a good chance code like that is recognizable to you. We’ve got a chain of three functions nested together, each one representing a step in an asynchronous series (task, “process”).

This kind of code is often called callback hell, and sometimes also referred to as the pyramid of doom (for its sideways-facing triangular shape due to the nested indentation).

But callback hell actually has almost nothing to do with the nesting/indentation. It’s a far deeper problem than that. We’ll see how and why as we continue through the rest of this chapter.

First, we’re waiting for the click event, then we’re waiting for the timer to fire, then we’re waiting for the Ajax response to come back, at which point it might do it all again.

At first glance, this code may seem to map its asynchrony naturally to sequential brain planning.

First (now), we:

listen( "..", function handler(..){
    // ..
} );

Then later, we:

setTimeout( function request(..){
    // ..
}, 500) ;

Then still later, we:

ajax( "..", function response(..){
    // ..
} );

And finally (most later), we:

if ( .. ) {
    // ..
}
else ..

But there’s several problems with reasoning about this code linearly in such a fashion.

First, it’s an accident of the example that our steps are on subsequent lines (1, 2, 3, and 4…). In real async JS programs, there’s often a lot more noise cluttering things up, noise that we have to deftly maneuver past in our brains as we jump from one function to the next. Understanding the async flow in such callback-laden code is not impossible, but it’s certainly not natural or easy, even with lots of practice.

But also, there’s something deeper wrong, which isn’t evident just in that code example. Let me make up another scenario (pseudocode-ish) to illustrate it:

doA( function(){
    doB();

    doC( function(){
        doD();
    } )

    doE();
} );

doF();

While the experienced among you will correctly identify the true order of operations here, I’m betting it is more than a little confusing at first glance, and takes some concerted mental cycles to arrive at. The operations will happen in this order:

doA()

doF()

doB()

doC()

doE()

doD()

Did you get that right the very first time you glanced at the code?

OK, some of you are thinking I was unfair in my function naming, to intentionally lead you astray. I swear I was just naming in top-down appearance order. But let me try again:

doA( function(){
    doC();

    doD( function(){
        doF();
    } )

    doE();
} );

doB();

Now, I’ve named them alphabetically in order of actual execution. But I still bet, even with experience now in this scenario, tracing through the A → B → C → D → E → F order doesn’t come naturally. Certainly your eyes do an awful lot of jumping up and down the code snippet, right?

But even if that all comes naturally to you, there’s still one more hazard that could wreak havoc. Can you spot what it is?

What if doA(..) or doD(..) aren’t actually async, the way we obviously assumed them to be? Uh-oh, now the order is different. If they’re both in sync (and maybe only sometimes, depending on the conditions of the program at the time), the order is now A → C → D → F → E → B.

That sound you just heard faintly in the background is the sighs of thousands of JS developers who just had a face-in-hands moment.

Is nesting the problem? Is that what makes it so hard to trace the async flow? That’s part of it, certainly.

But let me rewrite the previous nested event/timeout/Ajax example without using nesting:

listen( "click", handler );

function handler() {
    setTimeout( request, 500 );
}

function request(){
    ajax( "http://some.url.1", response );
}

function response(text){
    if (text == "hello") {
        handler();
    }
    else if (text == "world") {
        request();
    }
}

This formulation of the code is not hardly as recognizable as having the nesting/indentation woes of its previous form, and yet it’s every bit as susceptible to callback hell. Why?

As we go to linearly (sequentially) reason about this code, we have to skip from one function, to the next, to the next, and bounce all around the code base to “see” the sequence flow. And remember, this is simplified code in sort of best-case fashion. We all know that real async JS program code bases are often fantastically more jumbled, which makes such reasoning orders of magnitude more difficult.

Another thing to notice: to get steps 2, 3, and 4 linked together so they happen in succession, the only affordance callbacks alone gives us is to hardcode step 2 into step 1, step 3 into step 2, step 4 into step 3, and so on. The hardcoding isn’t necessarily a bad thing, if it really is a fixed condition that step 2 should always lead to step 3.

But the hardcoding definitely makes the code a bit more brittle, as it doesn’t account for anything going wrong that might cause a deviation in the progression of steps. For example, if step 2 fails, step 3 never gets reached, nor does step 2 retry, or move to an alternate error handling flow, and so on.

All of these issues are things you can manually hardcode into each step, but that code is often very repetitive and not reusable in other steps or in other async flows in your program.

Even though our brains might plan out a series of tasks in a sequential type of way (this, then this, then this), the evented nature of our brain operation makes recovery/retry/forking of flow control almost effortless. If you’re out running errands, and you realize you left a shopping list at home, it doesn’t end the day because you didn’t plan that ahead of time. Your brain routes around this hiccup easily: you go home, get the list, then head right back out to the store.

But the brittle nature of manually hardcoded callbacks (even with hardcoded error handling) is often far less graceful. Once you end up specifying (aka pre-planning) all the various eventualities/paths, the code becomes so convoluted that it’s hard to ever maintain or update it.

That is what callback hell is all about! The nesting/indentations are basically a side show, a red herring.

And as if all that’s not enough, we haven’t even touched what happens when two or more chains of these callback continuations are happening simultaneously, or when the third step branches out into parallel callbacks with gates or latches, or…OMG, my brain hurts, how about yours!?

Are you catching the notion here that our sequential, blocking brain planning behaviors just don’t map well onto callback-oriented async code? That’s the first major deficiency of callbacks: they express asynchrony in code in ways our brains have to fight just to keep in sync with (pun intended!).

Trust Issues

The mismatch between sequential brain planning and callback-driven async JS code is only part of the problem with callbacks. There’s something much deeper to be concerned about.

Let’s once again revisit the notion of a callback function as the continuation (aka the second half) of our program:

// A
ajax( "..", function(..){
    // C
} );
// B

// A and // B happen now, under the direct control of the main JS program. But // C gets deferred to happen later, and under the control of another party—in this case, the ajax(..) function. In a basic sense, that sort of hand-off of control doesn’t regularly cause lots of problems for programs.

But don’t be fooled by its infrequency and assume that this control switch isn’t a big deal. In fact, it’s one of the worst (and yet most subtle) problems with callback-driven design. It revolves around the idea that sometimes ajax(..) (i.e., the party you hand your callback continuation to) is not a function that you wrote, or that you directly control. Many times it’s a utility provided by some third party.

We call this inversion of control, when you take part of your program and give over control of its execution to another third party. There’s an unspoken contract that exists between your code and the third-party utility—a set of things you expect to be maintained.

Tale of Five Callbacks

It might not be terribly obvious why this is such a big deal. Let me construct an exaggerated scenario to illustrate the hazards of trust at play.

Imagine you’re a developer tasked with building out an ecommerce checkout system for a site that sells expensive TVs. You already have all the various pages of the checkout system built out just fine. On the last page, when the user clicks “confirm” to buy the TV, you need to call a third-party function (provided, say, by some analytics tracking company) so that the sale can be tracked.

You notice that they’ve provided what looks like an async tracking utility, probably for the sake of performance best practices, which means you need to pass in a callback function. In this continuation that you pass in, you will have the final code that charges the customer’s credit card and displays the thank you page.

This code might look like:

analytics.trackPurchase( purchaseData, function(){
    chargeCreditCard();
    displayThankyouPage();
} );

Easy enough, right? You write the code, test it, everything works, and you deploy to production. Everyone’s happy!

Six months go by and no issues. You’ve almost forgotten you even wrote that code. One morning, you’re at a coffee shop before work, casually enjoying your latte, when you get a panicked call from your boss insisting you drop the coffee and rush into work right away.

When you arrive, you find out that a high-profile customer has had his credit card charged five times for the same TV, and he’s understandably upset. Customer service has already issued an apology and processed a refund. But your boss demands to know how this could possibly have happened. “Don’t we have tests for stuff like this!?”

You don’t even remember the code you wrote. But you dig back in and start trying to find out what could have gone awry.

After digging through some logs, you come to the conclusion that the only explanation is that the analytics utility somehow, for some reason, called your callback five times instead of once. Nothing in their documentation mentions anything about this.

Frustrated, you contact customer support, who of course is as astonished as you are. They agree to escalate it to their developers, and promise to get back to you. The next day, you receive a lengthy email explaining what they found, which you promptly forward to your boss.

Apparently, the developers at the analytics company had been working on some experimental code that, under certain conditions, would retry the provided callback once per second, for five seconds, before failing with a timeout. They had never intended to push that into production, but somehow they did, and they’re totally embarrassed and apologetic. They go into plenty of detail about how they’ve identified the breakdown and what they’ll do to ensure it never happens again. Yadda, yadda.

What’s next?

You talk it over with your boss, but he’s not feeling particularly comfortable with the state of things. He insists, and you reluctantly agree, that you can’t trust them anymore (that’s what bit you), and that you’ll need to figure out how to protect the checkout code from such a vulnerability again.

After some tinkering, you implement some simple ad hoc code like the following, which the team seems happy with:

var tracked = false;

analytics.trackPurchase( purchaseData, function(){
    if (!tracked) {
        tracked = true;
        chargeCreditCard();
        displayThankyouPage();
    }
} );

Note

This should look familiar to you from Chapter 1, because we’re essentially creating a latch to handle any multiple concurrent invocations of our callback.

But then one of your QA engineers asks, “what happens if they never call the callback?” Oops. Neither of you had thought about that.

You begin to chase down the rabbit hole, and think of all the possible things that could go wrong with them calling your callback. Here’s roughly the list you come up with of ways the analytics utility could misbehave:

Call the callback too early (before it’s been tracked)

Call the callback too late (or never)

Call the callback too few or too many times (like the problem you encountered!)

Fail to pass along any necessary environment/parameters to your callback

Swallow any errors/exceptions that may happen

…

That should feel like a troubling list, because it is. You’re probably slowly starting to realize that you’re going to have to invent an awful lot of ad hoc logic in each and every single callback that’s passed to a utility you’re not positive you can trust.

Now you realize a bit more completely just how hellish callback hell is.

Review

Callbacks are the fundamental unit of asynchrony in JS. But they’re not enough for the evolving landscape of async programming as JS matures.

First, our brains plan things out in sequential, blocking, single-threaded semantic ways, but callbacks express asynchronous flow in a rather nonlinear, nonsequential way, which makes reasoning properly about such code much harder. Hard-to-reason-about code is bad code that leads to bad bugs.

We need a way to express asynchrony in a more synchronous, sequential, blocking manner, just like our brains do.

Second, and more importantly, callbacks suffer from inversion of control in that they implicitly give control over to another party (often a third-party utility not in your control!) to invoke the continuation of your program. This control transfer leads us to a troubling list of trust issues, such as whether the callback is called more times than we expect.

Inventing ad hoc logic to solve these trust issues is possible, but it’s more difficult than it should be, and it produces code that is clunkier, harder to maintain, and likely insufficiently protected from these hazards until you get visibly bitten by the bugs.

We need a generalized solution to all of the trust issues, one that can be reused for as many callbacks as we create without all the extra boilerplate overhead.

We need something better than callbacks. They’ve served us well to this point, but the future of JavaScript demands more sophisticated and capable async patterns. The subsequent chapters in this book dive into those emerging evolutions.

Chapter 3. Promises

In Chapter 2, we identified two major categories of deficiencies with using callbacks to express program asynchrony and manage concurrency: lack of sequentiality and lack of trustability. Now that we understand the problems more intimately, it’s time we turn our attention to patterns that can address them.

The issue we want to address first is the inversion of control, the trust that is so fragilely held and so easily lost.

Recall that we wrap up the continuation of our program in a callback function, and hand that callback over to another party (potentially even external code) and just cross our fingers that it will do the right thing with the invocation of the callback.

We do this because we want to say, “here’s what happens later, after the current step finishes.”

But what if we could uninvert that inversion of control? What if, instead of handing the continuation of our program to another party, we could expect it to return us a capability to know when its task finishes, and then our code could decide what to do next?

This paradigm is called Promises.

Promises are starting to take the JS world by storm, as developers and specification writers alike desperately seek to untangle the insanity of callback hell in their code/design. In fact, most new async APIs being added to the JS/DOM platform are being built on Promises. So it’s probably a good idea to dig in and learn them, don’t you think!?

Note

The word “immediately” is used frequently in this chapter, generally to refer to some Promise resolution action. However, in essentially all cases, “immediately” means in terms of the Job queue behavior (see Chapter 1), not in the strictly synchronous now sense.

Future Value

Imagine this scenario: I walk up to the counter at a fast-food restaurant, and place an order for a cheeseburger. I hand the cashier $1.47. By placing my order and paying for it, I’ve made a request for a value back (the cheeseburger). I’ve started a transaction.

But often, the chesseburger is not immediately available for me. The cashier hands me something in place of my cheeseburger: a receipt with an order number on it. This order number is an IOU (“I owe you”) promise that ensures that I should eventually receive my cheeseburger.

So I hold onto my receipt and order number. I know it represents my future cheeseburger, so I don’t need to worry about it anymore—aside from being hungry!

While I wait, I can do other things, like send a text message to a friend that says, “Hey, can you come join me for lunch? I’m going to eat a cheeseburger.”

I am reasoning about my future cheeseburger already, even though I don’t have it in my hands yet. My brain is able to do this because it’s treating the order number as a placeholder for the cheeseburger. The placeholder essentially makes the value time independent. It’s a future value.

Eventually, I hear, “order 113!” and I gleefully walk back up to the counter with receipt in hand. I hand my receipt to the cashier, and I take my cheeseburger in return.

In other words, once my future value was ready, I exchanged my value-promise for the value itself.

But there’s another possible outcome. They call my order number, but when I go to retrieve my cheeseburger, the cashier regretfully informs me, “I’m sorry, but we appear to be all out of cheeseburgers.” Setting aside the customer frustration of this scenario for a moment, we can see an important characteristic of future values: they can either indicate a success or failure.

Every time I order a cheeseburger, I know that I’ll either get a cheeseburger eventually, or I’ll get the sad news of the cheeseburger shortage, and I’ll have to figure out something else to eat for lunch.

Note

In code, things are not quite as simple, because metaphorically the order number may never be called, in which case we’re left indefinitely in an unresolved state. We’ll come back to dealing with that case later.

Values Now and Later

This all might sound too mentally abstract to apply to your code. So let’s be more concrete.

However, before we can introduce how Promises work in this fashion, we’re going to derive in code that we already understand—callbacks!—how to handle these future values.

When you write code to reason about a value, such as performing math on a number, whether you realize it or not, you’ve been assuming something very fundamental about that value, which is that it’s a concrete now value already:

var x, y = 2;

console.log( x + y ); // NaN  <-- because `x` isn't set yet

The x + y operation assumes both x and y are already set. In terms we’ll expound on shortly, we assume the x and y values are already resolved.

It would be nonsense to expect that the + operator by itself would somehow be magically capable of detecting and waiting around until both x and y are resolved (aka ready), and only then do the operation. That would cause chaos in the program if different statements finished now and others finished later, right?

How could you possibly reason about the relationships between two statements if either one (or both) of them might not be finished yet? If statement 2 relies on statement 1 being finished, there are just two outcomes: either statement 1 finished right now and everything proceeds fine, or statement 1 didn’t finish yet, and thus statement 2 is going to fail.

If this sort of thing sounds familiar from Chapter 1, good!

Let’s go back to our x + y math operation. Imagine if there was a way to say, “Add x and y, but if either of them isn’t ready yet, just wait until they are. Add them as soon as you can.”

Your brain might have just jumped to callbacks. OK, so…

function add(getX,getY,cb) {
    var x, y;
    getX( function(xVal){
        x = xVal;
        // both are ready?
        if (y != undefined) {
            cb( x + y );    // send along sum
        }
    } );
    getY( function(yVal){
        y = yVal;
        // both are ready?
        if (x != undefined) {
            cb( x + y );    // send along sum
        }
    } );
}

// `fetchX()` and `fetchY()` are sync or async
// functions
add( fetchX, fetchY, function(sum){
    console.log( sum ); // that was easy, huh?
} );

Take just a moment to let the beauty (or lack thereof) of that snippet sink in (whistles patiently).

While the ugliness is undeniable, there’s something very important about this async pattern.

In that snippet, we treated x and y as future values, and we express an operation add(..) that (from the outside) does not care whether x or y or both are available right away. In other words, it normalizes the now and later, such that we can rely on a predictable outcome of the add(..) operation.

By using an add(..) that is temporally consistent—it behaves the same across now and later times—the async code is much easier to reason about.

To put it more plainly: to consistently handle both now and later, we make both of them later: all operations become async.

Of course, this rough callbacks-based approach leaves much to be desired. It’s just a first tiny step toward realizing the benefits of reasoning about future values without worrying about the time aspect of when it’s available or not.

Promise Value

We’ll definitely go into a lot more detail about Promises later in the chapter—so don’t worry if some of this is confusing—but let’s just briefly glimpse at how we can express the x + y example via Promises functions:

function add(xPromise,yPromise) {
    // `Promise.all([ .. ])` takes an array of promises,
    // and returns a new promise that waits on them
    // all to finish
    return Promise.all( [xPromise, yPromise] )

    // when that promise is resolved, let's take the
    // received `X` and `Y` values and add them together.
    .then( function(values){
        // `values` is an array of the messages from the
        // previously resolved promises
        return values[0] + values[1];
    } );
}

// `fetchX()` and `fetchY()` return promises for
// their respective values, which may be ready
// now or later.
add( fetchX(), fetchY() )

// we get a promise back for the sum of those
// two numbers.
// now we chain-call `then(..)` to wait for the
// resolution of that returned promise.
.then( function(sum){
    console.log( sum ); // that was easier!
} );

There are two layers of Promises in this snippet.

fetchX() and fetchY() are called directly, and the values they return (promises!) are passed into add(..). The underlying values those promises represent may be ready now or later, but each promise normalizes the behavior to be the same regardless. We reason about X and Y values in a time-independent way. They are future values.

The second layer is the promise that add(..) creates (via Promise.all([ .. ])) and returns, which we wait on by calling then(..). When the add(..) operation completes, our sum future value is ready and we can print it out. We hide inside of add(..) the logic for waiting on the X and Y future values.

Note

Inside add(..), the Promise.all([ .. ]) call creates a promise (which is waiting on promiseX and promiseY to resolve). The chained call to .then(..) creates another promise, which the return values[0] + values[1] line immediately resolves (with the result of the addition). Thus, the then(..) call we chain off the end of the add(..) call—at the end of the snippet—is actually operating on that second promise returned, rather than the first one created by Promise.all([ .. ]). Also, though we are not chaining off the end of that second then(..), it too has created another promise, had we chosen to observe/use it. This Promise chaining stuff will be explained in much greater detail later in this chapter.

Just like with cheeseburger orders, it’s possible that the resolution of a Promise is rejection instead of fulfillment. Unlike a fulfilled Promise, where the value is always programmatic, a rejection value—commonly called a rejection reason—can either be set directly by the program logic, or it can result implicitly from a runtime exception.

With Promises, the then(..) call can actually take two functions, the first for fulfillment (as shown earlier), and the second for rejection:

add( fetchX(), fetchY() )
.then(
    // fullfillment handler
    function(sum) {
        console.log( sum );
    },
    // rejection handler
    function(err) {
        console.error( err ); // bummer!
    }
);

If something went wrong getting X or Y, or something somehow failed during the addition, the promise that add(..) returns is rejected, and the second callback error handler passed to then(..) will receive the rejection value from the promise.

Because Promises encapsulate the time-dependent state—waiting on the fulfillment or rejection of the underlying value—from the outside, the Promise itself is time-independent, and thus Promises can be composed (combined) in predictable ways regardless of the timing or outcome underneath.

Moreover, once a Promise is resolved, it stays that way forever—it becomes an immutable value at that point—and can then be observed as many times as necessary.

Note

Because a Promise is externally immutable once resolved, it’s now safe to pass that value around to any party and know that it cannot be modified accidentally or maliciously. This is especially true in relation to multiple parties observing the resolution of a Promise. It is not possible for one party to affect another party’s ability to observe Promise resolution. Immutability may sound like an academic topic, but it’s actually one of the most fundamental and important aspects of Promise design, and shouldn’t be casually passed over.

That’s one of the most powerful and important concepts to understand about Promises. With a fair amount of work, you could ad hoc create the same effects with nothing but ugly callback composition, but that’s not really an effective strategy, especially because you have to do it over and over again.

Promises are an easily repeatable mechanism for encapsulating and composing future values.

Completion Event

As we just saw, an individual Promise behaves as a future value. But there’s another way to think of the resolution of a Promise: as a flow-control mechanism—a temporal this-then-that—for two or more steps in an asynchronous task.

Let’s imagine calling a function foo(..) to perform some task. We don’t know about any of its details, nor do we care. It may complete the task right away, or it may take a while.

We just simply need to know when foo(..) finishes so that we can move on to our next task. In other words, we’d like a way to be notified of foo(..)’s completion so that we can continue.

In typical JavaScript fashion, if you need to listen for a notification, you’d likely think of that in terms of events. So we could reframe our need for notification as a need to listen for a completion event (or continuation event) emitted by foo(..).

Note

Whether you call it a completion or a continuation event depends on your perspective. Is the focus more on what happens with foo(..), or what happens after foo(..) finishes? Both perspectives are accurate and useful. The event notification tells us that foo(..) has completed, but also that it’s OK to continue with the next step. Indeed, the callback you pass to be called for the event notification is itself what we’ve previously called a continuation. The completion event is a bit more focused on the foo(..), which has our attention at present, so we call it a completion event for the rest of this text.

With callbacks, the notification would be our callback invoked by the task (foo(..)). But with Promises, we turn the relationship around, and expect that we can listen for an event from foo(..), and when notified, proceed accordingly.

First, consider some pseudocode:

foo(x) {
    // start doing something that could take a while
}

foo( 42 )

on (foo "completion") {
    // now we can do the next step!
}

on (foo "error") {
    // oops, something went wrong in `foo(..)`
}

We call foo(..) and then we set up two event listeners, one for "completion" and one for "error"—the two possible final outcomes of the foo(..) call. In essence, foo(..) doesn’t even appear to be aware that the calling code has subscribed to these events, which makes for a very nice separation of concerns.

Unfortunately, such code would require some magic of the JS environment that doesn’t exist (and would likely be a bit impractical). Here’s the more natural way we could express that in JS:

function foo(x) {
    // start doing something that could take a while

    // make a `listener` event notification
    // capability to return

    return listener;
}

var evt = foo( 42 );

evt.on( "completion", function(){
    // now we can do the next step!
} );

evt.on( "failure", function(err){
    // oops, something went wrong in `foo(..)`
} );

foo(..) expressly creates an event subscription capability to return back, and the calling code receives and registers the two event handlers against it.

The inversion from normal callback-oriented code should be obvious, and it’s intentional. Instead of passing the callbacks to foo(..), it returns an event capability we call evt, which receives the callbacks.

But if you recall from Chapter 2, callbacks themselves represent an inversion of control. So inverting the callback pattern is actually an inversion of inversion, or an uninversion of control—restoring control back to the calling code where we wanted it to be in the first place.

One important benefit is that multiple separate parts of the code can be given the event listening capability, and they can all independently be notified when foo(..) completes, in order to perform subsequent steps:

var evt = foo( 42 );

// let `bar(..)` listen to `foo(..)`'s completion
bar( evt );

// also, let `baz(..)` listen to `foo(..)`'s completion
baz( evt );

Uninversion of control enables a nicer separation of concerns, where bar(..) and baz(..) don’t need to be involved in how foo(..) is called. Similarly, foo(..) doesn’t need to know or care that bar(..) and baz(..) exist or are waiting to be notified when foo(..) completes.

Essentially, this evt object is a neutral third-party negotiation between the separate concerns.

Promise “Events”

As you may have guessed by now, the evt event listening capability is an analogy for a Promise.

In a Promise-based approach, the previous snippet would have foo(..) creating and returning a Promise instance, and that promise would then be passed to bar(..) and baz(..).

Note

The Promise resolution “events” we listen for aren’t strictly events (though they certainly behave like events for these purposes), and they’re not typically called "completion" or "error". Instead, we use then(..) to register a "then" event. Or perhaps more precisely, then(..) registers "fulfillment" and/or "rejection" event(s), though we don’t see those terms used explicitly in the code.

Consider:

function foo(x) {
    // start doing something that could take a while

    // construct and return a promise
    return new Promise( function(resolve,reject){
        // eventually, call `resolve(..)` or `reject(..)`,
        // which are the resolution callbacks for
        // the promise.
    } );
}

var p = foo( 42 );

bar( p );

baz( p );

Note

The pattern shown with new Promise( function(..){ .. } ) is generally called the revealing constructor. The function passed in is executed immediately (not async deferred, as callbacks to then(..) are), and it’s provided two parameters, which in this case we’ve named resolve and reject. These are the resolution functions for the promise. resolve(..) generally signals fulfillment, and reject(..) signals rejection.

You can probably guess what the internals of bar(..) and baz(..) might look like:

function bar(fooPromise) {
    // listen for `foo(..)` to complete
    fooPromise.then(
        function(){
            // `foo(..)` has now finished, so
            // do `bar(..)`'s task
        },
        function(){
            // oops, something went wrong in `foo(..)`
        }
    );
}

// ditto for `baz(..)`

Promise resolution doesn’t necessarily need to involve sending along a message, as it did when we were examining Promises as future values. It can just be a flow-control signal, as used in the previous snippet.

Another way to approach this is:

function bar() {
    // `foo(..)` has definitely finished, so
    // do `bar(..)`'s task
}

function oopsBar() {
    // oops, something went wrong in `foo(..)`,
    // so `bar(..)` didn't run
}

// ditto for `baz()` and `oopsBaz()`

var p = foo( 42 );

p.then( bar, oopsBar );

p.then( baz, oopsBaz );

Note

If you’ve seen Promise-based coding before, you might be tempted to believe that the last two lines of that code could be written as p.then( .. ).then( .. ), using chaining, rather than p.then(..); p.then(..). That would have an entirely different behavior, so be careful! The difference might not be clear right now, but it’s actually a different async pattern than we’ve seen thus far: splitting/forking. Don’t worry! We’ll come back to this point later in this chapter.

Instead of passing the p promise to bar(..) and baz(..), we use the promise to control when bar(..) and baz(..) will get executed, if ever. The primary difference is in the error handling.

In the first snippet’s approach, bar(..) is called regardless of whether foo(..) succeeds or fails, and it handles its own fallback logic if it’s notified that foo(..) failed. The same is true for baz(..), obviously.

In the second snippet, bar(..) gets called only if foo(..) succeeds, and otherwise oopsBar(..) gets called. Ditto for baz(..).

Neither approach is correct per se. There will be cases where one is preferred over the other.

In either case, the promise p that comes back from foo(..) is used to control what happens next.

Moreover, the fact that both snippets end up calling then(..) twice against the same promise p illustrates the point made earlier, which is that Promises (once resolved) retain their same resolution (fulfillment or rejection) forever, and can subsequently be observed as many times as necessary.

Whenever p is resolved, the next step will always be the same, both now and later.

Thenable Duck Typing

In Promises-land, an important detail is how to know for sure if some value is a genuine Promise or not. Or more directly, is it a value that will behave like a Promise?

Given that Promises are constructed by the new Promise(..) syntax, you might think that p instanceof Promise would be an acceptable check. But unfortunately, there are a number of reasons that’s not totally sufficient.

Mainly, you can receive a Promise value from another browser window (iframe, etc.), which would have its own Promise different from the one in the current window/frame, and that check would fail to identify the Promise instance.

Moreover, a library or framework may choose to vend its own Promises and not use the native ES6 Promise implementation to do so. In fact, you may very well be using Promises with libraries in older browsers that have no Promise at all.

When we discuss Promise resolution processes later in this chapter, it will become more obvious why it is still very important to be able to recognize and assimilate a Promise-like value that is not genuine. But for now, just take my word for it that it’s a critical piece of the puzzle.

As such, it was decided that the way to recognize a Promise (or something that behaves like a Promise) would be to define something called a thenable as any object or function which has a then(..) method on it. It is assumed that any such value is a Promise-conforming thenable.

The general term for type checks that make assumptions about a value’s type based on its shape (what properties are present) is called duck typing—“If it looks like a duck, and quacks like a duck, it must be a duck” (see the Types & Grammar title of this series). So the duck typing check for a thenable would roughly be:

if (
    p !== null &&
    (
        typeof p === "object" ||
        typeof p === "function"
    ) &&
    typeof p.then === "function"
) {
    // assume it's a thenable!
}
else {
    // not a thenable
}

Yuck! Setting aside the fact that this logic is a bit ugly to implement in various places, there’s something deeper and more troubling going on.

If you try to fulfill a Promise with any object/function value that happens to have a then(..) function on it, but you weren’t intending it to be treated as a Promise/thenable, you’re out of luck, because it will automatically be recognized as thenable and treated with special rules (see later in the chapter).

This is even true if you didn’t realize the value has a then(..) on it. For example:

var o = { then: function(){} };

// make `v` be `[[Prototype]]`-linked to `o`
var v = Object.create( o );

v.someStuff = "cool";
v.otherStuff = "not so cool";

v.hasOwnProperty( "then" );     // false

v doesn’t look like a Promise or thenable at all. It’s just a plain object with some properties on it. You’re probably just intending to send that value around like any other object.

But unknown to you, v is also [[Prototype]]-linked (see the this & Object Prototypes title of this series) to another object o, which happens to have a then(..) on it. So the thenable duck typing checks will think and assume v is a thenable. Uh-oh.

It doesn’t even need to be something as directly intentional as that:

Object.prototype.then = function(){};
Array.prototype.then = function(){};

var v1 = { hello: "world" };
var v2 = [ "Hello", "World" ];

Both v1 and v2 will be assumed to be thenables. You can’t control or predict if any other code accidentally or maliciously adds then(..) to Object.prototype, Array.prototype, or any of the other native prototypes. And if what’s specified is a function that doesn’t call either of its parameters as callbacks, then any Promise resolved with such a value will just silently hang forever! Crazy.

Sound implausible or unlikely? Perhaps.

But keep in mind that there were several well-known non-Promise libraries preexisting in the community prior to ES6 that happened to already have a method on them called then(..). Some of those libraries chose to rename their own methods to avoid collision (that sucks!). Others have simply been relegated to the unfortunate status of “incompatible with Promise-based coding” in reward for their inability to change to get out of the way.

The standards decision to hijack the previously nonreserved—and completely general-purpose sounding—then property name means that no value (or any of its delegates), either past, present, or future, can have a then(..) function present, either on purpose or by accident, or that value will be confused for a thenable in Promises systems, which will probably create bugs that are really hard to track down.

Warning

I do not like how we ended up with duck typing of thenables for Promise recognition. There were other options, such as “branding” or even “anti-branding”; what we got seems like a worst-case compromise. But it’s not all doom and gloom. Thenable duck typing can be helpful, as we’ll see later. Just beware that thenable duck typing can be hazardous if it incorrectly identifies something as a Promise that isn’t.

Failing to Pass Along Any Parameters/Environment

Promises can have, at most, one resolution value (fulfillment or rejection).

If you don’t explicitly resolve with a value either way, the value is undefined, as is typical in JS. But whatever the value, it will always be passed to all registered (and appropriate fulfillment or rejection) callbacks, either now or in the future.

Something to be aware of: If you call resolve(..) or reject(..) with multiple parameters, all subsequent parameters beyond the first will be silently ignored. Although that might seem a violation of the guarantee we just described, it’s not exactly, because it constitutes an invalid usage of the Promise mechanism. Other invalid usages of the API (such as calling resolve(..) multiple times) are similarly protected, so the Promise behavior here is consistent (if not a tiny bit frustrating).

If you want to pass along multiple values, you must wrap them in another single value that you pass, such as an array or an object.

As for environment, functions in JS always retain their closure of the scope in which they’re defined (see the Scope & Closures title of this series), so they of course would continue to have access to whatever surrounding state you provide. Of course, the same is true of callbacks-only design, so this isn’t a specific augmentation of benefit from Promises—but it’s a guarantee we can rely on nonetheless.

Pit of Despair

Jeff Atwood noted years ago that programming languages are often set up in such a way that, by default, developers fall into the “pit of despair”—where accidents are punished—and that you have to try harder to get it right. He implored us to instead create a “pit of success,” where by default you fall into expected (successful) action, and thus would have to try hard to fail.

Promise error handling is unquestionably “pit of despair” design. By default, it assumes that you want any error to be swallowed by the Promise state, and if you forget to observe that state, the error silently languishes/dies in obscurity—usually despair.

To avoid losing an error to the silence of a forgotten/discarded Promise, some developers have claimed that a best practice for Promise chains is to always end your chain with a final catch(..), like:

var p = Promise.resolve( 42 );

p.then(
    function fulfilled(msg){
        // numbers don't have string functions,
        // so will throw an error
        console.log( msg.toLowerCase() );
    }
)
.catch( handleErrors );

Because we didn’t pass a rejection handler to the then(..), the default handler was substituted, which simply propagates the error to the next promise in the chain. As such, both errors that come into p, and errors that come after p in its resolution (like the msg.toLowerCase() one) will filter down to the final handleErrors(..).

Problem solved, right? Not so fast!

What happens if handleErrors(..) itself also has an error in it? Who catches that? There’s still yet another unattended promise: the one catch(..) returns, which we don’t capture and don’t register a rejection handler for.

You can’t just stick another catch(..) on the end of that chain, because it too could fail. The last step in any Promise chain, whatever it is, always has the possibility, even decreasingly so, of dangling with an uncaught error stuck inside an unobserved Promise.

Sound like an impossible conundrum yet?

Uncaught Handling

It’s not exactly an easy problem to solve completely. There are other (many would say better) ways to approach it.

Some Promise libraries have added methods for registering something like a “global unhandled rejection” handler, which would be called instead of a globally thrown error. But their solution for how to identify an error as uncaught is to have an arbitrary-length timer, say three seconds, running from time of rejection. If a Promise is rejected but no error handler is registered before the timer fires, then it’s assumed that you won’t ever be registering a handler, so it’s uncaught.

In practice, this has worked well for many libraries, as most usage patterns don’t typically call for significant delay between Promise rejection and observation of that rejection. But this pattern is troublesome because three seconds is so arbitrary (even if empirical), and also because there are indeed some cases where you want a Promise to hold on to its rejectedness for some indefinite period of time, and you don’t really want to have your uncaught handler called for all those false positives (not-yet-handled uncaught errors).

Another more common suggestion is that Promises should have a done(..) added to them, which essentially marks the Promise chain as done. done(..) doesn’t create and return a Promise, so the callbacks passed to done(..) are obviously not wired up to report problems to a chained Promise that doesn’t exist.

So what happens instead? It’s treated as you might usually expect in uncaught error conditions: any exception inside a done(..) rejection handler would be thrown as a global uncaught error (in the developer console, basically):

var p = Promise.resolve( 42 );

p.then(
    function fulfilled(msg){
        // numbers don't have string functions,
        // so will throw an error
        console.log( msg.toLowerCase() );
    }
)
.done( null, handleErrors );

// if `handleErrors(..)` caused its own exception, it would
// be thrown globally here

This might sound more attractive than the never-ending chain or the arbitrary timeouts. But the biggest problem is that it’s not part of the ES6 standard, so no matter how good it sounds, at best it’s a lot longer way off from being a reliable and ubiquitous solution.

Are we just stuck, then? Not entirely.

Browsers have a unique capability that our code does not have: they can track and know for sure when any object gets thrown away and garbage collected. So, browsers can track Promise objects, and whenever they get garbage collected, if they have a rejection in them, the browser knows for sure this was a legitimate uncaught error, and can thus confidently know it should report it to the developer console.

Note

At the time of this writing, both Chrome and Firefox have early attempts at this sort of uncaught rejection capability, though support is incomplete at best.

However, if a Promise doesn’t get garbage collected—it’s exceedingly easy for that to accidentally happen through lots of different coding patterns—the browser’s garbage collection sniffing won’t help you know and diagnose that you have a silently rejected Promise laying around.

Is there any other alternative? Yes.

Pit of Success

The following is just theoretical, how Promises could be someday changed to behave. I believe it would be far superior to what we currently have. And I think this change would be possible even post-ES6 because I don’t think it would break web compatibility with ES6 Promises. Moreover, it can be polyfilled/prollyfilled in, if you’re careful. Let’s take a look:

Promises could default to reporting (to the developer console) any rejection, on the next Job or event loop tick, if at that exact moment no error handler has been registered for the Promise.

For the cases where you want a rejected Promise to hold onto its rejected state for an indefinite amount of time before observing, you could call defer(), which suppresses automatic error reporting on that Promise.

If a Promise is rejected, it defaults to noisily reporting that fact to the developer console (instead of defaulting to silence). You can opt out of that reporting either implicitly (by registering an error handler before rejection), or explicitly (with defer()). In either case, you control the false positives.

Consider:

var p = Promise.reject( "Oops" ).defer();

// `foo(..)` is Promise-aware
foo( 42 )
.then(
    function fulfilled(){
        return p;
    },
    function rejected(err){
        // handle `foo(..)` error
    }
);
...

When we create p, we know we’re going to wait a while to use/observe its rejection, so we call defer()—thus no global reporting. defer() simply returns the same promise, for chaining purposes.

The promise returned from foo(..) gets an error handler attached right away, so it’s implicitly opted out and no global reporting for it occurs either.

But the promise returned from the then(..) call has no defer() or error handler attached, so if it rejects (from inside either resolution handler), then it will be reported to the developer console as an uncaught error.

This design is a pit of success. By default, all errors are either handled or reported—what almost all developers in almost all cases would expect. You either have to register a handler or you have to intentionally opt out, and indicate you intend to defer error handling until later; you’re opting for the extra responsibility in just that specific case.

The only real danger in this approach is if you defer() a Promise but then fail to actually ever observe/handle its rejection.

But you had to intentionally call defer() to opt into that pit of despair—the default was the pit of success—so there’s not much else we could do to save you from your own mistakes.

I think there’s still hope for Promise error handling (post-ES6). I hope the powers that be will rethink the situation and consider this alternative. In the meantime, you can implement this yourself (a challenging exercise for the reader!), or use a smarter Promise library that does so for you!

Note

This exact model for error handling/reporting is implemented in my asynquence Promise abstraction library, which is discussed in Appendix A of this book.

Sequence Error Handling

We covered Promise-flavored error handling in detail earlier in this chapter. The limitations of how Promises are designed—how they chain, specifically—creates a very easy pitfall where an error in a Promise chain can be silently ignored accidentally.

But there’s something else to consider with Promise errors. Because a Promise chain is nothing more than its constituent Promises wired together, there’s no entity to refer to the entire chain as a single thing, which means there’s no external way to observe any errors that may occur.

If you construct a Promise chain that has no error handling in it, any error anywhere in the chain will propagate indefinitely down the chain, until observed (by registering a rejection handler at some step). So, in that specific case, having a reference to the last promise in the chain is enough (p in the following snippet), because you can register a rejection handler there, and it will be notified of any propagated errors:

// foo(..), STEP2(..) and STEP3(..) are
// all promise-aware utilities

var p = foo( 42 )
.then( STEP2 )
.then( STEP3 );

Although it may seem sneakily confusing, p here doesn’t point to the first promise in the chain (the one from the foo(42) call), but instead from the last promise, the one that comes from the then(STEP3) call.

Also, no step in the Promise chain is observably doing its own error handling. That means that you could then register a rejection error handler on p, and it would be notified if any errors occur anywhere in the chain:

p.catch( handleErrors );

But if any step of the chain in fact does its own error handling (perhaps hidden/abstracted away from what you can see), your handleErrors(..) won’t be notified. This may be what you want—it was, after all, a “handled rejection”—but it also may not be what you want. The complete lack of ability to be notified (of “already handled” rejection errors) is a limitation that restricts capabilities in some use cases.

It’s basically the same limitation that exists with a try..catch that can catch an exception and simply swallow it. So this isn’t a limitation unique to Promises, but it is something we might wish to have a workaround for.

Unfortunately, many times there is no reference kept for the intermediate steps in a Promise-chain sequence, so without such references, you cannot attach error handlers to reliably observe the errors.

Promise Performance

This particular limitation is both simple and complex.

Comparing how many pieces are moving with a basic callback-based async task chain versus a Promise chain, it’s clear Promises have a fair bit more going on, which means they are naturally at least a tiny bit slower. Think back to just the simple list of trust guarantees that Promises offer, as compared to the ad hoc solution code you’d have to layer on top of callbacks to achieve the same protections.

More work to do, more guards to protect, means that Promises are slower as compared to naked, untrustable callbacks. That much is obvious, and probably simple to wrap your brain around.

But how much slower? Well…that’s actually proving to be an incredibly difficult question to answer absolutely, across the board.

Frankly, it’s kind of an apples-to-oranges comparison, so it’s probably the wrong question to ask. You should actually compare whether an ad hoc callback system with all the same protections manually layered in is faster than a Promise implementation.

If Promises have a legitimate performance limitation, it’s more that they don’t really offer a line-item choice as to which trustability protections you want/need or not—you get them all, always.

Nevertheless, if we grant that a Promise is generally a little bit slower than its non-Promise, non-trustable callback equivalent—assuming there are places where you feel you can justify the lack of trustability—does that mean that Promises should be avoided across the board, as if your entire application is driven by nothing but must-be-utterly-the-fastest code possible?

Sanity check: if your code is legitimately like that, is JavaScript even the right language for such tasks? JavaScript can be optimized to run applications very performantly (see Chapters 5 and 6). But is obsessing over tiny performance tradeoffs with Promises, in light of all the benefits they offer, really appropriate?

Another subtle issue is that Promises make everything async, which means that some immediately (synchronously) complete steps still defer advancement of the next step to a Job (see Chapter 1). That means that it’s possible that a sequence of Promise tasks could complete ever-so-slightly slower than the same sequence wired up with callbacks.

Of course, the question here is this: are these potential slips in tiny fractions of performance worth all the other articulated benefits of Promises we’ve laid out across this chapter?

My take is that in virtually all cases where you might think Promise performance is slow enough to be concerned, it’s actually an anti-pattern to optimize away the benefits of Promise trustability and composability by avoiding them altogether.

Instead, you should default to using them across the code base, and then profile and analyze your application’s hot (critical) paths. Are Promises really a bottleneck, or are they just a theoretical slowdown? Only then, armed with actual valid benchmarks (see Chapter 6) is it responsible and prudent to factor out the Promises in just those identified critical areas.

Promises are a little slower, but in exchange you’re getting a lot of trustability, non-Zalgo predictability, and composability built in. Maybe the limitation is not actually their performance, but your lack of perception of their benefits?

Breaking Run-to-Completion

In Chapter 1, we explained an expectation that JS developers almost universally rely on in their code: once a function starts executing, it runs until it completes, and no other code can interrupt and run in between.

As bizarre as it may seem, ES6 introduces a new type of function that does not behave with the run-to-completion behavior. This new type of function is called a generator.

To understand the implications, let’s consider this example:

var x = 1;

function foo() {
    x++;
    bar();              // <-- what about this line?
    console.log( "x:", x );
}

function bar() {
    x++;
}

foo();                  // x: 3

In this example, we know for sure that bar() runs in between x++ and console.log(x). But what if bar() wasn’t there? Obviously the result would be 2 instead of 3.

Now let’s twist your brain. What if bar() wasn’t present, but it could still somehow run between the x++ and console.log(x) statements? How would that be possible?

In preemptive multithreaded languages, it would essentially be possible for bar() to interrupt and run at exactly the right moment between those two statements. But JS is not preemptive, nor is it (currently) multithreaded. And yet, a cooperative form of this interruption (concurrency) is possible, if foo() itself could somehow indicate a pause at that part in the code.

Note

I use the word “cooperative” not only because of the connection to classical concurrency terminology (see Chapter 1), but because as you’ll see in the next snippet, the ES6 syntax for indicating a pause point in code is yield—suggesting a politely cooperative yielding of control.

Here’s the ES6 code to accomplish such cooperative concurrency:

var x = 1;

function *foo() {
    x++;
    yield; // pause!
    console.log( "x:", x );
}

function bar() {
    x++;
}

Note

You will likely see most other JS documentation/code that will format a generator declaration as function* foo() { .. } instead of as I’ve done here with function *foo() { .. }—the only difference being the stylistic positioning of the *. The two forms are functionally/syntactically identical, as is a third function*foo() { .. } (no space) form. There are arguments for both styles, but I basically prefer function *foo.. because it then matches when I reference a generator in writing with *foo(). If I said only foo(), you wouldn’t know as clearly if I was talking about a generator or a regular function. It’s purely a stylistic preference.

Now, how can we run the code in that previous snippet such that bar() executes at the point of the yield inside of *foo()?

// construct an iterator `it` to control the generator
var it = foo();

// start `foo()` here!
it.next();
x;                      // 2
bar();
x;                      // 3
it.next();              // x: 3

OK, there’s quite a bit of new and potentially confusing stuff in those two code snippets, so we’ve got plenty to wade through. But before we explain the different mechanics/syntax with ES6 generators, let’s walk through the behavior flow:

The it = foo() operation does not execute the *foo() generator yet, but it merely constructs an iterator that will control its execution. More on iterators in a bit.

The first it.next() starts the *foo() generator, and runs the x++ on the first line of *foo().

*foo() pauses at the yield statement, at which point that first it.next() call finishes. At the moment, *foo() is still running and active, but it’s in a paused state.

We inspect the value of x, and it’s now 2.

We call bar(), which increments x again with x++.

We inspect the value of x again, and it’s now 3.

The final it.next() call resumes the *foo() generator from where it was paused, and runs the console.log(..) statement, which uses the current value of x of 3.

Clearly, foo() started, but did not run-to-completion—it paused at the yield. We resumed foo() later, and let it finish, but that wasn’t even required.

So, a generator is a special kind of function that can start and stop one or more times, and doesn’t necessarily ever have to finish. While it won’t be terribly obvious yet why that’s so powerful, as we go throughout the rest of this chapter, that will be one of the fundamental building blocks we use to construct generators-as-async-flow-control as a pattern for our code.

Input and Output

A generator function is a special function with the new processing model we just alluded to. But it’s still a function, which means it still has some basic tenets that haven’t changed—namely, that it still accepts arguments (aka input), and that it can still return a value (aka output):

function *foo(x,y) {
    return x * y;
}

var it = foo( 6, 7 );

var res = it.next();

res.value;      // 42

We pass in the arguments 6 and 7 to *foo(..) as the parameters x and y, respectively. And *foo(..) returns the value 42 back to the calling code.

We now see a difference with how the generator is invoked compared to a normal function. foo(6,7) obviously looks familiar. But subtly, the *foo(..) generator hasn’t actually run yet as it would have with a function.

Instead, we’re just creating an iterator object, which we assign to the variable it, to control the *foo(..) generator. Then we call it.next(), which instructs the *foo(..) generator to advance from its current location, stopping either at the next yield or end of the generator.

The result of that next(..) call is an object with a value property on it holding whatever value (if anything) was returned from *foo(..). In other words, yield caused a value to be sent out from the generator during the middle of its execution, kind of like an intermediate return.

Again, it won’t be obvious yet why we need this whole indirect iterator object to control the generator. We’ll get there, I promise.

Iteration Messaging

In addition to generators accepting arguments and having return values, there’s even more powerful and compelling input/output messaging capability built into them, via yield and next(..).

Consider:

function *foo(x) {
    var y = x * (yield);
    return y;
}

var it = foo( 6 );

// start `foo(..)`
it.next();

var res = it.next( 7 );

res.value;      // 42

First, we pass in 6 as the parameter x. Then we call it.next(), and it starts up *foo(..).

Inside *foo(..), the var y = x .. statement starts to be processed, but then it runs across a yield expression. At that point, it pauses *foo(..) (in the middle of the assignment statement!), and essentially requests the calling code to provide a result value for the yield expression. Next, we call it.next( 7 ), which is passing the 7 value back in to be that result of the paused yield expression.

So, at this point, the assignment statement is essentially var y = 6 * 7. Now, return y returns that 42 value back as the result of the it.next( 7 ) call.

Notice something very important but also easily confusing, even to seasoned JS developers: depending on your perspective, there’s a mismatch between the yield and the next(..) call. In general, you’re going to have one more next(..) call than you have yield statements—the preceding snippet has one yield and two next(..) calls.

Why the mismatch?

Because the first next(..) always starts a generator, and runs to the first yield. But it’s the second next(..) call that fulfills the first paused yield expression, and the third next(..) would fulfill the second yield, and so on.

Tale of Two Questions

Actually, which code you’re thinking about primarily will affect whether there’s a perceived mismatch or not.

Consider only the generator code:

var y = x * (yield);
return y;

This first yield is basically asking a question: “What value should I insert here?”

Who’s going to answer that question? Well, the first next() has already run to get the generator up to this point, so obviously it can’t answer the question. So, the second next(..) call must answer the question posed by the first yield.

See the mismatch—second-to-first?

But let’s flip our perspective. Let’s look at it not from the generator’s point of view, but from the iterator’s point of view.

To properly illustrate this perspective, we also need to explain that messages can go in both directions—yield .. as an expression can send out messages in response to next(..) calls, and next(..) can send values to a paused yield expression. Consider this slightly adjusted code:

function *foo(x) {
    var y = x * (yield "Hello");    // <-- yield a value!
    return y;
}

var it = foo( 6 );

var res = it.next();    // first `next()`, don't pass anything
res.value;              // "Hello"

res = it.next( 7 );     // pass `7` to waiting `yield`
res.value;              // 42

yield .. and next(..) pair together as a two-way message passing system during the execution of the generator.

So, looking only at the iterator code:

var res = it.next();    // first `next()`, don't pass anything
res.value;              // "Hello"

res = it.next( 7 );     // pass `7` to waiting `yield`
res.value;              // 42

Note

We don’t pass a value to the first next() call, and that’s on purpose. Only a paused yield could accept such a value passed by a next(..), and at the beginning of the generator when we call the first next(), there is no paused yield to accept such a value. The specification and all compliant browsers just silently discard anything passed to the first next(). It’s still a bad idea to pass a value, as you’re just creating silently failing code that’s confusing. So, always start a generator with an argument-free next().

The first next() call (with nothing passed to it) is basically asking a question: “What next value does the *foo(..) generator have to give me?” And who answers this question? The first yield "hello" expression.

See? No mismatch there.

Depending on who you think about asking the question, there is either a mismatch between the yield and next(..) calls, or not.

But wait! There’s still an extra next() compared to the number of yield statements. So, that final it.next(7) call is again asking the question about what next value the generator will produce. But there’s no more yield statements left to answer, is there? So who answers?

The return statement answers the question!

And if there is no return in your generator—return is certainly not any more required in generators than in regular functions—there’s always an assumed/implicit return; (aka return undefined;), which serves the purpose of default answering the question posed by the final it.next(7) call.

These questions and answers—the two-way message passing with yield and next(..)—are quite powerful, but it’s not obvious at all how these mechanisms are connected to async flow control. We’re getting there!

Review

Generators are a new ES6 function type that does not run-to-completion like normal functions. Instead, the generator can be paused in mid-completion (entirely preserving its state), and it can later be resumed from where it left off.

This pause/resume interchange is cooperative rather than preemptive, which means that the generator has the sole capability to pause itself, using the yield keyword, and yet the iterator that controls the generator has the sole capability (via next(..)) to resume the generator.

The yield / next(..) duality is not just a control mechanism, it’s actually a two-way message passing mechanism. A yield .. expression essentially pauses waiting for a value, and the next next(..) call passes a value (or implicit undefined) back to that paused yield expression.

The key benefit of generators related to async flow control is that the code inside a generator expresses a sequence of steps for the task in a naturally sync/sequential fashion. The trick is that we essentially hide potential asynchrony behind the yield keyword—moving the asynchrony to the code where the generator’s iterator is controlled.

In other words, generators preserve a sequential, synchronous, blocking code pattern for async code, which lets our brains reason about the code much more naturally, addressing one of the two key drawbacks of callback-based async.

Chapter 5. Program Performance

This book so far has been all about how to leverage asynchrony patterns more effectively. But we haven’t directly addressed why asynchrony really matters to JS. The most obvious explicit reason is performance.

For example, if you have two Ajax requests to make, and they’re independent, but you need to wait on them both to finish before doing the next task, you have two options for modeling that interaction: serial and concurrent.

You could make the first request and wait to start the second request until the first finishes. Or, as we’ve seen both with promises and generators, you could make both requests in parallel, and ask the gate to wait on both of them before moving on.

Clearly, the latter is usually going to be more performant than the former. And better performance generally leads to better user experience.

It’s even possible that asynchrony (interleaved concurrency) can improve just the perception of performance, even if the overall program still takes the same amount of time to complete. User perception of performance is every bit—if not more!—as important as actual measurable performance.

We want to now move beyond localized asynchrony patterns to talk about some bigger picture performance details at the program level.

Note

You may be wondering about micro-performance issues, like if a++ or ++a is faster. We’ll look at those sorts of performance details in Chapter 6.

Web Workers

If you have processing-intensive tasks but you don’t want them to run on the main thread (which may slow down the browser/UI), you might have wished that JavaScript could operate in a multithreaded manner.

In Chapter 1, we talked in detail about how JavaScript is single threaded. And that’s still true. But a single thread isn’t the only way to organize the execution of your program.

Imagine splitting your program into two pieces, and running one of those pieces on the main UI thread, and running the other piece on an entirely separate thread.

What kinds of concerns would such an architecture bring up?

For one, you’d want to know if running on a separate thread meant that it ran in parallel (on systems with multiple CPUs/cores) such that a long-running process on that second thread would not block the main program thread. Otherwise, “virtual threading” wouldn’t be of much benefit over what we already have in JS with async concurrency.

And you’d want to know if these two pieces of the program have access to the same shared scope/resources. If they do, then you have all the questions that multithreaded languages (Java, C++, etc.) deal with, such as needing cooperative or preemptive locking (mutexes, etc.). That’s a lot of extra work, and shouldn’t be undertaken lightly.

Alternatively, you’d want to know how these two pieces could communicate if they couldn’t share scope/resources.

All these are great questions to consider as we explore a feature added to the web platform circa HTML5 called Web Workers. This is a feature of the browser (aka host environment) and actually has almost nothing to do with the JS language itself. That is, JavaScript does not currently have any features that support threaded execution.

But an environment like your browser can easily provide multiple instances of the JavaScript engine, each on its own thread, and let you run a different program in each thread. Each of those separate threaded pieces of your program is called a (Web) Worker. This type of parallelism is called task parallelism, as the emphasis is on splitting up chunks of your program to run in parallel.

From your main JS program (or another Worker), you instantiate a Worker like so:

var w1 = new Worker( "http://some.url.1/mycoolworker.js" );

The URL should point to the location of a JS file (not an HTML page!) which is intended to be loaded into a Worker. The browser will then spin up a separate thread and let that file run as an independent program in that thread.

Note

The kind of Worker created with such a URL is called a Dedicated Worker. But instead of providing a URL to an external file, you can also create an Inline Worker by providing a Blob URL (another HTML5 feature); essentially it’s an inline file stored in a single (binary) value. However, Blobs are beyond the scope of what we’ll discuss here.

Workers do not share any scope or resources with each other or the main program—that would bring all the nightmares of theaded programming to the forefront—but instead have a basic event messaging mechanism connecting them.

The w1 Worker object is an event listener and trigger, which lets you subscribe to events sent by the Worker as well as send events to the Worker.

Here’s how to listen for events (actually, the fixed "message" event):

w1.addEventListener( "message", function(evt){
    // evt.data
} );

And you can send the "message" event to the Worker:

w1.postMessage( "something cool to say" );

Inside the Worker, the messaging is totally symmetrical:

// "mycoolworker.js"

addEventListener( "message", function(evt){
    // evt.data
} );

postMessage( "a really cool reply" );

Notice that a dedicated Worker is in a one-to-one relationship with the program that created it. That is, the "message" event doesn’t need any disambiguation here, because we’re sure that it could only have come from this one-to-one relationship—it came from either the Worker or the main page.

Usually the main page application creates the Workers, but a Worker can instantiate its own child Worker(s)—known as subworkers—as necessary. Sometimes this is useful to delegate such details to a sort of “master” Worker that spawns other Workers to process parts of a task. Unfortunately, at the time of this writing, Chrome still does not support subworkers, while Firefox does.

To kill a Worker immediately from the program that created it, call terminate() on the Worker object (like w1 in the previous snippets). Abruptly terminating a Worker thread does not give it any chance to finish up its work or clean up any resources. It’s akin to you closing a browser tab to kill a page.

If you have two or more pages (or multiple tabs with the same page!) in the browser that try to create a Worker from the same file URL, those will actually end up as completely separate Workers. Shortly, we’ll discuss a way to share a Worker.

Note

It may seem like a malicious or ignorant JS program could easily perform a denial-of-service attack on a system by spawning hundreds of Workers, seemingly each with their own thread. While it’s true that it’s somewhat of a guarantee that a Worker will end up on a separate thread, this guarantee is not unlimited. The system is free to decide how many actual threads/CPUs/cores it really wants to create. There’s no way to predict or guarantee how many you’ll have access to, though many people assume it’s at least as many as the number of CPUs/cores available. I think the safest assumption is that there’s at least one other thread besides the main UI thread, but that’s about it.

Worker Environment

Inside the Worker, you do not have access to any of the main program’s resources. That means you cannot access any of its global variables, nor can you access the page’s DOM or other resources. Remember: it’s a totally separate thread.

You can, however, perform network operations (Ajax, WebSockets) and set timers. Also, the Worker has access to its own copy of several important global variables/features, including navigator, location, JSON, and applicationCache.

You can also load extra JS scripts into your Worker, using importScripts(..):

// inside the Worker
importScripts( "foo.js", "bar.js" );

These scripts are loaded synchronously, which means the importScripts(..) call will block the rest of the Worker’s execution until the file(s) are finished loading and executing.

Note

There have also been some discussions about exposing the <canvas> API to Workers, which combined with having canvases be Transferables (see “Data Transfer”), would allow Workers to perform more sophisticated off-thread graphics processing, which can be useful for high-performance gaming (WebGL) and other similar applications. Although this doesn’t exist yet in any browsers, it’s likely to happen in the near future.

What are some common uses for Web Workers?

Processing intensive math calculations

Sorting large data sets

Data operations (compression, audio analysis, image pixel manipulations, etc.)

High-traffic network communications

Data Transfer

You may notice a common characteristic of most of those uses, which is that they require a large amount of information to be transferred across the barrier between threads using the event mechanism, perhaps in both directions.

In the early days of Workers, serializing all data to a string value was the only option. In addition to the speed penalty of the two-way serializations, the other major negative was that the data was being copied, which meant a doubling of memory usage (and the subsequent churn of garbage collection).

Thankfully, we now have a few better options.

If you pass an object, a structured clone algorithm is used to copy/duplicate the object on the other side. This algorithm is fairly sophisticated and can even handle duplicating objects with circular references. The to-string/from-string performance penalty is not paid, but we still have duplication of memory using this approach. There is support for this in IE10 and above, as well as all the other major browsers.

An even better option, especially for larger data sets, is Transferable Objects. What happens is that the object’s ownership is transferred, but the data itself is not moved. Once you transfer away an object to a Worker, it’s empty or inaccessible in the the originating location—that eliminates the hazards of threaded programming over a shared scope. Of course, transfer of ownership can go in both directions.

There really isn’t much you need to do to opt into a Transferable Object; any data structure that implements the Transferable interface will automatically be transferred this way (supported in Firefox & Chrome).

For example, typed arrays like Uint8Array (see the ES6 & Beyond title of this series) are Transferables. This is how you’d send a Transferable Object using postMessage(..):

// `foo` is a `Uint8Array` for instance

postMessage( foo.buffer, [ foo.buffer ] );

The first parameter is the raw buffer and the second parameter is a list of what to transfer.

Browsers that don’t support Transferable Objects simply degrade to structured cloning, which means performance reduction rather than outright feature breakage.

Polyfilling Web Workers

Web Workers are very attractive performance-wise for running JS programs in parallel. However, you may be in a position where your code needs to run in older browsers that lack support. Because Workers are an API and not a syntax, they can be polyfilled, to an extent.

If a browser doesn’t support Workers, there’s simply no way to fake multithreading from the performance perspective. Iframes are commonly thought of to provide a parallel environment, but in all modern browsers they actually run on the same thread as the main page, so they’re not sufficient for faking parallelism.

As we detailed in Chapter 1, JS’s asynchronicity (not parallelism) comes from the event loop queue, so you can force faked Workers to be asynchronous using timers (setTimeout(..), etc.). Then you just need to provide a polyfill for the Worker API. There are some listed on the Modernizr GitHub page, but frankly none of them look great.

I’ve written a sketch of a polyfill for Worker on this gist. It’s basic, but it should get the job done for simple Worker support, given that the two-way messaging works correctly as well as "onerror" handling. You could probably also extend it with more features, such as terminate() or faked Shared Workers, as you see fit.

Note

You can’t fake synchronous blocking, so this polyfill just disallows use of importScripts(..). Another option might have been to parse and transform the Worker’s code (once Ajax loaded) to handle rewriting to some asynchronous form of an importScripts(..) polyfill, perhaps with a promise-aware interface.

Review

The first four chapters of this book are based on the premise that async coding patterns give you the ability to write more performant code, which is generally a very important improvement. But async behavior only gets you so far, because it’s still fundamentally bound to a single event loop thread.

So in this chapter we’ve covered several program-level mechanisms for improving performance even further.

Web Workers let you run a JS file (aka program) in a separate thread using async events to message between the threads. They’re wonderful for offloading long-running or resource-intensive tasks to a different thread, leaving the main UI thread more responsive.

SIMD proposes to map CPU-level parallel math operations to JavaScript APIs for high-performance data-parallel operations, like number processing on large data sets.

Finally, asm.js describes a small subset of JavaScript that avoids the hard-to-optimize parts of JS (like garbage collection and coercion) and lets the JS engine recognize and run such code through aggressive optimizations. asm.js could be hand authored, but that’s extremely tedious and error prone, akin to hand authoring assembly language (hence the name). Instead, the main intent is that asm.js would be a good target for cross-compilation from other highly optimized program languages—for example, Emscripten transpiling C/C++ to JavaScript.

While not covered explicitly in this chapter, there are even more radical ideas under very early discussion for JavaScript, including approximations of direct threaded functionality (not just hidden behind data structure APIs). Whether that happens explicitly, or we just see more parallelism creep into JS behind the scenes, the future of more optimized program-level performance in JS looks really promising.

Benchmarking

OK, time to start dispelling some misconceptions. I’d wager the vast majority of JS developers, if asked to benchmark the speed (execution time) of a certain operation, would initially go about it something like this:

var start = (new Date()).getTime(); // or `Date.now()`

// do some operation

var end = (new Date()).getTime();

console.log( "Duration:", (end - start) );

Raise your hand if that’s roughly what came to your mind. Yep, I thought so. There’s a lot wrong with this approach, but don’t feel bad; we’ve all been there.

What did that measurement tell you, exactly? Understanding what it does and doesn’t say about the execution time of the operation in question is key to learning how to appropriately benchmark performance in JavaScript.

If the duration reported is 0, you may be tempted to believe that it took less than a millisecond. But that’s not very accurate. Some platforms don’t have single millisecond precision, but instead only update the timer in larger increments. For example, older versions of windows (and thus IE) had only 15ms precision, which means the operation has to take at least that long for anything other than 0 to be reported!

Moreover, whatever duration is reported, the only thing you really know is that the operation took approximately that long on that exact single run. You have near-zero confidence that it will always run at that speed. You have no idea if the engine or system had some sort of interference at that exact moment, and that at other times the operation could run faster.

What if the duration reported is 4? Are you more sure it took about four milliseconds? Nope. It might have taken less time, and there may have been some other delay in getting either start or end timestamps.

More troublingly, you also don’t know that the circumstances of this operation test aren’t overly optimistic. It’s possible that the JS engine figured out a way to optimize your isolated test case, but in a more real program such optimization would be diluted or impossible, such that the operation would run slower than your test.

So…what do we know? Unfortunately, with those realizations stated, we know very little. Something of such low confidence isn’t even remotely good enough to build your determinations on. Your benchmark is basically useless. And worse, it’s dangerous in that it implies false confidence, not just to you but also to others who don’t think critically about the conditions that led to those results.

Repetition

“OK,” you now say, “just put a loop around it so the whole test takes longer.” If you repeat an operation 100 times, and that whole loop reportedly takes a total of 137ms, then you can just divide by 100 and get an average duration of 1.37ms for each operation, right?

Well, not exactly.

A straight mathematical average by itself is definitely not sufficient for making judgments about performance which you plan to extrapolate to the breadth of your entire application. With a hundred iterations, even a couple of outliers (high or low) can skew the average, and then when you apply that conclusion repeatedly, you even further inflate the skew beyond credulity.

Instead of just running for a fixed number of iterations, you can instead choose to run the loop of tests until a certain amount of time has passed. That might be more reliable, but how do you decide how long to run? You might guess that it should be some multiple of how long your operation should take to run once. Wrong.

Actually, the length of time to repeat across should be based on the accuracy of the timer you’re using, specifically to minimize the chances of inaccuracy. The less precise your timer, the longer you need to run to make sure you’ve minimized the error percentage. A 15ms timer is pretty bad for accurate benchmarking; to minimize its uncertainty (aka error rate) to less than 1%, you need to run your each cycle of test iterations for 750ms. A 1ms timer needs a cycle to run for only 50ms to get the same confidence.

But then, that’s just a single sample. To be sure you’re factoring out the skew, you’ll want lots of samples to average across. You’ll also want to understand something about just how slow the worst sample is, how fast the best sample is, how far apart those best and worse cases were, and so on. You’ll want to know not just a number that tells you how fast something ran, but also to have some quantifiable measure of how trustable that number is.

Also, you probably want to combine these different techniques (as well as others), so that you get the best balance of all the possible approaches.

That’s all the bare minimum just to get started. If you’ve been approaching performance benchmarking in a less serious manner than what I just glossed over, well…you don’t know: proper benchmarking.

Benchmark.js

Any relevant and reliable benchmark should be based on statistically sound practices. I am not going to write a chapter on statistics here, so I’ll hand wave around some terms: standard deviation, variance, margin of error. If you don’t know what those terms really mean—I took a stats class back in college and I’m still a little fuzzy on them—you are not actually qualified to write your own benchmarking logic.

Luckily, smart folks like John-David Dalton and Mathias Bynens do understand these concepts, and wrote a statistically sound benchmarking tool called Benchmark.js. So I can end the suspense by simply saying: “just use that tool.”

I won’t repeat their whole documentation for how Benchmark.js works; they have fantastic API docs you should read. Also there are some great writeups on more of the details and methodology here and here.

But just for quick illustration purposes, here’s how you could use Benchmark.js to run a quick performance test:

function foo() {
    // operation(s) to test
}

var bench = new Benchmark(
    "foo test",             // test name
    foo,                    // function to test (just contents)
    {
        // ..               // optional extra options (see docs)
    }
);

bench.hz;                   // number of operations per second
bench.stats.moe;            // margin of error
bench.stats.variance;       // variance across samples
// ..

There’s lots more to learn about using Benchmark.js besides this glance I’m including here. But the point is that it’s handling all of the complexities of setting up a fair, reliable, and valid performance benchmark for a given piece of JavaScript code. If you’re going to try to test and benchmark your code, this library is the first place you should turn.

We’re showing here the usage to test a single operation like X, but it’s fairly common that you want to compare X to Y. This is easy to do by simply setting up two different tests in a suite (a Benchmark.js organizational feature). Then, you run them head-to-head, and compare the statistics to conclude whether X or Y was faster.

Benchmark.js can of course be used to test JavaScript in a browser (see “jsPerf.com” later in this chapter), but it can also run in nonbrowser environments (Node.js, etc.).

One largely untapped potential use-case for Benchmark.js is to use it in your Dev or QA environments to run automated performance regression tests against critical path parts of your application’s JavaScript. Similar to how you might run unit test suites before deployment, you can also compare the performance against previous benchmarks to monitor if you are improving or degrading application performance.

Setup/Teardown

In the previous code snippet, we glossed over the “extra options” { .. } object. But there are two options we should discuss: setup and teardown.

These two options let you define functions to be called before and after your test case runs.

It’s incredibly important to understand that your setup and teardown code does not run for each test iteration. The best way to think about it is that there’s an outer loop (repeating cycles), and an inner loop (repeating test iterations). setup and teardown are run at the beginning and end of each outer loop (aka cycle) iteration, but not inside the inner loop.

Why does this matter? Let’s imagine you have a test case that looks like this:

a = a + "w";
b = a.charAt( 1 );

Then, you set up your test setup as follows:

var a = "x";

Your temptation is probably to believe that a is starting out as "x" for each test iteration.

But it’s not! It’s starting a at "x" for each test cycle, and then your repeated + "w" concatenations will be making a larger and larger a value, even though you’re only ever accessing the character "w" at the 1 position.

Where this most commonly bites you is when you make side effect changes to something like the DOM, like appending a child element. You may think your parent element is set as empty each time, but it’s actually getting lots of elements added, and that can significantly sway the results of your tests.

Context Is King

Don’t forget to check the context of a particular performance benchmark, especially a comparison between X and Y tasks. Just because your test reveals that X is faster than Y doesn’t mean that the conclusion “X is faster than Y” is actually relevant.

For example, let’s say a performance test reveals that X runs 10,000,000 operations per second, and Y runs at 8,000,000 operations per second. You could claim that Y is 20% slower than X, and you’d be mathematically correct, but your assertion doesn’t hold as much water as you’d think.

Let’s think about the results more critically: 10,000,000 operations per second is 10,000 operations per millisecond, and 10 operations per microsecond. In other words, a single operation takes 0.1 microseconds, or 100 nanoseconds. It’s hard to fathom just how small 100ns is, but for comparison, it’s often cited that the human eye isn’t generally capable of distinguishing anything less than 100ms, which is one million times slower than the 100ns speed of the X operation.

Even recent scientific studies showing that maybe the brain can process as quick as 13ms (about 8x faster than previously asserted) would mean that X is still running 125,000 times faster than the human brain can perceive a distinct thing happening. X is going really, really fast.

But more importantly, let’s talk about the difference between X and Y, the 2,000,000 operations per second difference. If X takes 100ns, and Y takes 80ns, the difference is 20ns, which in the best case is still one 650-thousandth of the interval the human brain can perceive.

What’s my point? None of this performance difference matters, at all!

But wait, what if this operation is going to happen a whole bunch of times in a row? Then the difference could add up, right?

OK, so what we’re asking then is, how likely is it that operation X is going to be run over and over again, one right after the other, and that this has to happen 650,000 times just to get a sliver of a hope the human brain could perceive it. More likely, it’d have to happen 5,000,000 to 10,000,000 times together in a tight loop to even approach relevance.

While the computer scientist in you might protest that this is possible, the louder voice of realism in you should sanity check just how likely or unlikely that really is. Even if it is relevant in rare occasions, it’s irrelevant in most situations.

The vast majority of your benchmark results on tiny operations—like the ++x vs x++ myth—are just totally bogus for supporting the conclusion that X should be favored over Y on a performance basis.

Engine Optimizations

You simply cannot reliably extrapolate that if X was 10 microseconds faster than Y in your isolated test, that means X is always faster than Y and should always be used. That’s not how performance works. It’s vastly more complicated.

For example, let’s imagine (purely hypothetical) that you test some microperformance behavior such as comparing:

var twelve = "12";
var foo = "foo";

// test 1
var X1 = parseInt( twelve );
var X2 = parseInt( foo );

// test 2
var Y1 = Number( twelve );
var Y2 = Number( foo );

If you understand what parseInt(..) does compared to Number(..), you might intuit that parseInt(..) potentially has more work to do, especially in the foo case. Or you might intuit that they should have the same amount of work to do in the foo case, as both should be able to stop at the first character, f.

Which intuition is correct? I honestly don’t know. But I’ll make the case it doesn’t matter what your intuition is. What might the results be when you test it? Again, I’m making up a pure hypothetical here; I haven’t actually tried testing this, nor do I care to.

Let’s pretend the test comes back that X and Y are statistically identical. Have you then confirmed your intuition about the f character thing? Nope.

It’s possible in our hypothetical that the engine might recognize that the variables twelve and foo are being used in only one place in each test, and so it might decide to inline those values. Then it may realize that Number( "12" ) can just be replaced by 12. And maybe it comes to the same conclusion with parseInt(..), or maybe not.

Or an engine’s dead-code removal heuristic could kick in, and it could realize that variables X and Y aren’t being used, so declaring them is irrelevant, so it doesn’t end up doing anything at all in either test.

And all that’s just made with the mindset of assumptions about a single test run. Modern engines are fantastically more complicated than what we’re intuiting here. They do all sorts of tricks, like tracing and tracking how a piece of code behaves over a short period of time, or with a particularly constrained set of inputs.

What if the engine optimizes a certain way because of the fixed input, but in your real program you give more varied input and the optimization decisions shake out differently (or not at all!)? Or what if the engine kicks in optimizations because it sees the code being run tens of thousands of times by the benchmarking utility, but in your real program it will only run a hundred times in near proximity, and under those conditions the engine determines the optimizations are not worth it?

And all those optimizations we just hypothesized about might happen in our constrained test but maybe the engine wouldn’t do them in a more complex program (for various reasons). Or it could be reversed—the engine might not optimize such trivial code but may be more inclined to optimize it more aggressively when the system is already more taxed by a more sophisticated program.

The point I’m trying to make is that you really don’t know for sure exactly what’s going on under the covers. All the guesses and hypothesis you can muster don’t amount to anything concrete for making such decisions.

Does that mean you can’t really do any useful testing? Definitely not!

What this boils down to is that testing not real code gives you not real results. If possible and practical, you should test actual real, nontrivial snippets of your code, and under as best of real conditions as you can actually hope to. Only then will the results you get have a chance to approximate reality.

Microbenchmarks like ++x vs x++ are so incredibly likely to be bogus, we might as well just flatly assume them as such.

Writing Good Tests

Let me see if I can articulate the bigger point I’m trying to make here.

Good test authoring requires careful analytical thinking about what differences exist between two test cases and whether the differences between them are intentional or unintentional.

Intentional differences are of course normal and OK, but it’s too easy to create unintentional differences that skew your results. You have to be really, really careful to avoid that skew. Moreover, you may intend a difference but it may not be obvious to other readers of your test what your intent was, so they may doubt (or trust!) your test incorrectly. How do you fix that?

Write better, clearer tests. But also, take the time to document (using the jsPerf.com “Description” field and/or code comments) exactly what the intent of your test is, even to the nuanced detail. Call out the intentional differences, which will help others and your future self to better identify unintentional differences that could be skewing the test results.

Isolate things which aren’t relevant to your test by pre-declaring them in the page or test setup settings so they’re outside the timed parts of the test.

Instead of trying to narrow in on a tiny snippet of your real code and benchmarking just that piece out of context, tests and benchmarks are better when they include a larger (while still relevant) context. Those tests also tend to run slower, which means any differences you spot are more relevant in context.

Not All Engines Are Alike

The different JS engines in various browsers can all be “spec compliant” while having radically different ways of handling code. The JS specification doesn’t require anything performance related—well, except for ES6’s “tail call optimization,” covered in “Tail Call Optimization (TCO)”.

The engines are free to decide that one operation will receive its attention to optimize, perhaps trading off for lesser performance on another operation. It can be very tenuous to find an approach for an operation that always runs faster in all browsers.

There’s a movement among some in the JS dev community, especially those who work with Node.js, to analyze the specific internal implementation details of the v8 JavaScript engine and make decisions about writing JS code that is tailored to take best advantage of how v8 works. You can actually achieve a surprisingly high degree of performance optimization with such endeavors, so the payoff for the effort can be quite high.

Some commonly cited examples for v8 are as follows:

Don’t pass the arguments variable from one function to any other function, as such leakage slows down the function implementation.

Isolate a try..catch in its own function. Browsers struggle with optimizing any function with a try..catch in it, so moving that construct to its own function means you contain the de-optimization harm while letting the surrounding code be optimizable.

But rather than focus on those tips specifically, let’s sanity check the v8-only optimization approach in a general sense.

Are you genuinely writing code that needs to run in only one JS engine? Even if your code is entirely intended for Node.js right now, is the assumption that v8 will always be the used JS engine reliable? Is it possible that someday, a few years from now, there will be another server-side JS platform besides Node.js that you choose to run your code on? What if what you optimized for before is now a much slower way of doing that operation on the new engine?

Or what if your code always stays running on v8 from here on out, but v8 decides at some point to change the way some set of operations works such that what used to be fast is now slow, and vice versa?

These scenarios aren’t just theoretical, either. It used to be that it was faster to put multiple string values into an array and then call join("") on the array to concatenate the values than to just use + concatenation directly with the values. The historical reason for this is nuanced, but it has to do with internal implementation details about how string values were stored and managed in memory.

As a result, best practice advice at the time disseminated across the industry suggesting developers always use the array join(..) approach. And many followed.

Except, somewhere along the way, the JS engines changed approaches for internally managing strings, and specifically put in optimizations for + concatenation. They didn’t slow down join(..) per se, but they put more effort into helping + usage, as it was still quite a bit more widespread.

Note

The practice of standardizing or optimizing some particular approach based mostly on its existing widespread usage is often called (metaphorically) “paving the cowpath.”

Once that new approach to handling strings and concatenation took hold, unfortunately all the code out in the wild that was using array join(..) to concatenate strings was then suboptimal.

Another example: at one time, the Opera browser differed from other browsers in how it handled the boxing/unboxing of primitive wrapper objects (see the Types & Grammar title of this series). As such, their advice to developers was to use a String object instead of the primitive string value if properties like length or methods like charAt(..) needed to be accessed. This advice may have been correct for Opera at the time, but it was literally completely opposite for other major contemporary browsers, as they had optimizations specifically for the string primitives and not their object wrapper counterparts.

I think these various gotchas are at least possible, if not likely, for code even today. So I’m very cautious about making wide-ranging performance optimizations in my JS code based purely on engine implementation details, especially if those details are only true of a single engine.

The reverse is also something to be wary of: you shouldn’t necessarily change a piece of code to work around one engine’s difficulty with running a piece of code in an acceptably performant way.

Historically, IE has been the brunt of many such frustrations, given that there have been plenty of scenarios in older IE versions where it struggled with some performance aspect that other major browsers of the time seemed not to have much trouble with. The string concatenation discussion we just had was actually a real concern back in the IE6 and IE7 days, when it was possible to get better performance out of join(..) than +.

But it’s troublesome to suggest that just one browser’s trouble with performance is justification for using a code approach that quite possibly could be suboptimal in all other browsers. Even if the browser in question has a large market share for your site’s audience, it may be more practical to write the proper code and rely on the browser to update itself with better optimizations eventually.

“There is nothing more permanent than a temporary hack.” Chances are, the code you write now to work around some performance bug will probably outlive the performance bug in the browser itself.

In the days when a browser only updated once every five years, that was a tougher call to make. But as it stands now, browsers across the board are updated at a much more rapid interval (though obviously the mobile world still lags), and they’re all competing to optimize web features better and better.

If you run across a case where a browser does have a performance wart that others don’t suffer from, make sure to report the issue to its developers through whatever means you have available. Most browsers have open public bug trackers suitable for this purpose.

Tip

I’d suggest working around a performance issue in a browser only if it is a really drastic show-stopper, not just an annoyance or frustration. And I’d be very careful to check that the performance hack didn’t have noticeable negative side effects in another browser.

Big Picture

Instead of worrying about all these microperformance nuances, we should instead be looking at big-picture types of optimizations.

How do you know what’s big picture or not? You have to first understand if your code is running on a critical path. If it’s not on a critical path, chances are your optimizations are not worth much.

Ever heard the admonition, “that’s premature optimization!”? It comes from a famous quote from Donald Knuth: “premature optimization is the root of all evil.” Many developers cite this quote to suggest that most optimizations are “premature” and are thus a waste of effort. The truth is, as usual, more nuanced.

Here is Knuth’s quote, in context (emphasis added):

Programmers waste enormous amounts of time thinking about, or worrying about, the speed of noncritical parts of their programs, and these attempts at efficiency actually have a strong negative impact when debugging and maintenance are considered. We should forget about small efficiencies, say about 97% of the time: premature optimization is the root of all evil. Yet we should not pass up our opportunities in that critical 3%.

Computing Surveys 6 (December 1974)

I believe it’s a fair paraphrasing to say that Knuth meant: “non-critical path optimization is the root of all evil.” So the key is to figure out if your code is on a critical path—if it is, you should optimize it!

I’d even go so far as to say this: no amount of time spent optimizing critical paths is wasted, no matter how little is saved; but no amount of optimization on noncritical paths is justified, no matter how much is saved.

If your code is on a critical path, such as a “hot” piece of code that’s going to be run over and over again, or in UX critical places where users will notice, like an animation loop or CSS style updates, then you should spare no effort in trying to employ relevant, measurably significant optimizations.

For example, consider a critical path animation loop that needs to coerce a string value to a number. There are of course multiple ways to do that (see the Types & Grammar title of this series), but which one, if any, is the fastest?

var x = "42";   // need number `42`

// Option 1: let implicit coercion automatically happen
var y = x / 2;

// Option 2: use `parseInt(..)`
var y = parseInt( x, 0 ) / 2;

// Option 3: use `Number(..)`
var y = Number( x ) / 2;

// Option 4: use `+` unary operator
var y = +x / 2;

// Option 5: use `|` unary operator
var y = (x | 0) / 2;

Note

I will leave it as an exercise to the reader to set up a test if you’re interested in examining the minute differences in performance among these options.

When considering these different options, as they say, “One of these things is not like the others.” parseInt(..) does the job, but it also does a lot more—it parses the string rather than just coercing. You can probably guess, correctly, that parseInt(..) is a slower option, and you should probably avoid it.

Of course, if x can ever be a value that needs parsing, such as "42px" (like from a CSS style lookup), then parseInt(..) really is the only suitable option!

Number(..) is also a function call. From a behavioral perspective, it’s identical to the + unary operator option, but it may in fact be a little slower, requiring more machinery to execute the function. Of course, it’s also possible that the JS engine recognizes this behavioral symmetry and just handles the inlining of Number(..)’s behavior (aka +x) for you!

But remember, obsessing about +x versus x | 0 is in most cases a waste of effort. This is a microperformance issue, and one that you shouldn’t let dictate/degrade the readability of your program.

While performance is very important in critical paths of your program, it’s not the only factor. Among several options that are roughly similar in performance, readability should be another important concern.

Tail Call Optimization (TCO)

As we briefly mentioned earlier, ES6 includes a specific requirement that ventures into the world of performance. It’s related to a specific form of optimization that can occur with function calls: tail call optimization.

Briefly, a tail call is a function call that appears at the “tail” of another function, such that after the call finishes, there’s nothing left to do (except perhaps return its result value).

For example, here’s a nonrecursive setup with tail calls:

function foo(x) {
    return x;
}

function bar(y) {
    return foo( y + 1 );    // tail call
}

function baz() {
    return 1 + bar( 40 );   // not tail call
}

baz();                      // 42

foo(y+1) is a tail call in bar(..) because after foo(..) finishes, bar(..) is also finished and just needs to return the result of the foo(..) call. However, bar(40) is not a tail call because after it completes, its result value must be added to 1 before baz() can return it.

Without getting into too much nitty-gritty detail, calling a new function requires an extra amount of reserved memory to manage the call stack, called a stack frame. So the preceding snippet would generally require a stack frame for each of baz(), bar(..), and foo(..) all at the same time.

However, if a TCO-capable engine can realize that the foo(y+1) call is in tail position meaning bar(..) is basically complete, then when calling foo(..), it doesn’t need to create a new stack frame, but can instead reuse the existing stack frame from bar(..). That’s not only faster, but it also uses less memory.

That sort of optimization isn’t a big deal in a simple snippet, but it becomes a much bigger deal when dealing with recursion, especially if the recursion could have resulted in hundreds or thousands of stack frames. With TCO, the engine can perform all those calls with a single stack frame!

Recursion is a hairy topic in JS because without TCO, engines have had to implement arbitrary (and different!) limits to how deep they will let the recursion stack get before they stop it, to prevent running out of memory. With TCO, recursive functions with tail position calls can essentially run unbounded, because there’s never any extra usage of memory!

Consider that recursive factorial(..) from before, but rewritten to make it TCO-friendly:

function factorial(n) {
    function fact(n,res) {
        if (n < 2) return res;

        return fact( n - 1, n * res );
    }

    return fact( n, 1 );
}

factorial( 5 );     // 120

This version of factorial(..) is still recursive, but it’s also optimizable with TCO, because both inner fact(..) calls are in tail position.

Note

It’s important to note that TCO applies only if there’s actually a tail call. If you write recursive functions without tail calls, the performance will still fall back to normal stack frame allocation, and the engines’ limits on such recursive call stacks will still apply. Many recursive functions can be rewritten as we just showed with factorial(..), but it takes careful attention to detail.

One reason that ES6 requires engines to implement TCO rather than leaving it up to their discretion is because the lack of TCO actually tends to reduce the chances that certain algorithms will be implemented in JS using recursion, for fear of the call stack limits.

If the lack of TCO in the engine would just gracefully degrade to slower performance in all cases, it wouldn’t have been something that ES6 needed to require. But because the lack of TCO can actually make certain programs impractical, it’s more an important feature of the language than just a hidden implementation detail.

ES6 guarantees that from now on, JS developers will be able to rely on this optimization across all ES6+ compliant browsers. That’s a win for JS performance!

Review

Effectively benchmarking performance of a piece of code, especially to compare it to another option for that same code to see which approach is faster, requires careful attention to detail.

Rather than rolling your own statistically valid benchmarking logic, just use the Benchmark.js library, which does that for you. But be careful about how you author tests, because it’s far too easy to construct a test that seems valid but that’s actually flawed—even tiny differences can skew the results to be completely unreliable.

It’s important to get as many test results from as many different environments as possible to eliminate hardware/device bias. jsPerf.com is a fantastic website for crowdsourcing performance benchmark test runs.

Many common performance tests unfortunately obsess about irrelevant microperformance details like x++ versus ++x. Writing good tests means understanding how to focus on big picture concerns, like optimizing on a critical path, and avoiding falling into traps like different JS engines’ implementation details.

Tail call optimization (TCO) is a required optimization as of ES6 that will make some recursive patterns practical in JS where they would have been impossible otherwise. TCO allows a function call in the tail position of another function to execute without needing any extra resources, which means the engine no longer needs to place arbitrary restrictions on call stack depth for recursive algorithms.

Appendix A. asynquence Library

Chapters 1 and 2 went into quite a bit of detail about typical asynchronous programming patterns and how they’re commonly solved with callbacks. But we also saw why callbacks are fatally limited in capability, which led us to Chapters 3 and 4, with Promises and generators offering a much more solid, trustable, and reason-able base to build your asynchrony on.

I referenced my own asynchronous library asynquence—“async” + “sequence” = “asynquence”—several times in this book, and I want to now briefly explain how it works and why its unique design is important and helpful.

In Appendix B, we’ll explore some advanced async patterns, but you’ll probably want a library to make those palatable enough to be useful. We’ll use asynquence to express those patterns, so you’ll want to spend a little time here getting to know the library first.

asynquence is obviously not the only option for good async coding; certainly there are many great libraries in this space. But asynquence provides a unique perspective by combining the best of all these patterns into a single library, and moreover is built on a single basic abstraction: the (async) sequence.

My premise is that sophisticated JS programs often need bits and pieces of various different asynchronous patterns woven together, and this is usually left entirely up to each developer to figure out. Instead of having to bring in two or more different async libraries that focus on different aspects of asynchrony, asynquence unifies them into variated sequence steps, with just one core library to learn and deploy.

I believe the value is strong enough with asynquence to make async flow control programming with Promise-style semantics super easy to accomplish, so that’s why we’ll exclusively focus on that library here.

To begin, I’ll explain the design principles behind asynquence, and then we’ll illustrate how its API works with code examples.

Sequences and Abstraction Design

Understanding asynquence begins with understanding a fundamental abstraction: any series of steps for a task, whether they separately are synchronous or asynchronous, can be collectively thought of as a sequence. In other words, a sequence is a container that represents a task, and is comprised of individual (potentially async) steps to complete that task.

Each step in the sequence is controlled under the covers by a Promise (see Chapter 3). That is, every step you add to a sequence implicitly creates a Promise that is wired to the previous end of the sequence. Because of the semantics of Promises, every single step advancement in a sequence is asynchronous, even if you synchronously complete the step.

Moreover, a sequence will always proceed linearly from step to step, meaning that step 2 always comes after step 1 finishes, and so on.

Of course, a new sequence can be forked off an existing sequence, meaning the fork only occurs once the main sequence reaches that point in the flow. Sequences can also be combined in various ways, including having one sequence subsumed by another sequence at a particular point in the flow.

A sequence is kind of like a Promise chain. However, with Promise chains, there is no “handle” to grab that references the entire chain. Whichever Promise you have a reference to only represents the current step in the chain plus any other steps hanging off it. Essentially, you cannot hold a reference to a Promise chain unless you hold a reference to the first Promise in the chain.

There are many cases where it turns out to be quite useful to have a handle that references the entire sequence collectively. The most important of those cases is with sequence abort/cancel. As we covered extensively in Chapter 3, Promises themselves should never be able to be canceled, as this violates a fundamental design imperative: external immutability.

But sequences have no such immutability design principle, mostly because sequences are not passed around as future-value containers that need immutable value semantics. So sequences are the proper level of abstraction to handle abort/cancel behavior. asynquence sequences can be abort()ed at any time, and the sequence will stop at that point and not go for any reason.

There’s plenty more reasons to prefer a sequence abstraction on top of Promise chains for flow control purposes.

First, Promise chaining is a rather manual process—one that can get pretty tedious once you start creating and chaining Promises across a wide swath of your programs—and this tedium can act counterproductively to dissuade the developer from using Promises in places where they are quite appropriate.

Abstractions are meant to reduce boilerplate and tedium, so the sequence abstraction is a good solution to this problem. With Promises, your focus is on the individual step, and there’s little assumption that you will keep the chain going. With sequences, the opposite approach is taken, assuming the sequence will keep having more steps added indefinitely.

This abstraction complexity reduction is especially powerful when you start thinking about higher-order Promise patterns (beyond race([..]) and all([..]).

For example, in the middle of a sequence, you may want to express a step that is conceptually like a try..catch in that the step will always result in success, either the intended main success resolution or a positive nonerror signal for the caught error. Or, you might want to express a step that is like a retry/until loop, where it keeps trying the same step over and over until success occurs.

These sorts of abstractions are quite nontrivial to express using only Promise primitives, and doing so in the middle of an existing Promise chain is not pretty. But if you abstract your thinking to a sequence, and consider a step as a wrapper around a Promise, that step wrapper can hide such details, freeing you to think about the flow control in the most sensible way without being bothered by the details.

Second, and perhaps more importantly, thinking of async flow control in terms of steps in a sequence allows you to abstract out the details of what types of asynchronicity are involved with each individual step. Under the covers, a Promise will always control the step, but above the covers, that step can look either like a continuation callback (the simple default), or like a real Promise, or as a run-to-completion generator, or… Hopefully, you get the picture.

Third, sequences can more easily be twisted to adapt to different modes of thinking, such as event-, stream-, or reactive-based coding. asynquence provides a pattern I call reactive sequences (which we’ll cover later) as a variation on the reactive observable ideas in RxJS (Reactive Extensions), which lets a repeatable event fire off a new sequence instance each time. Promises are one-shot-only, so it’s quite awkward to express repetitious asynchrony with Promises alone.

Another alternate mode of thinking inverts the resolution/control capability in a pattern I call iterable sequences. Instead of each individual step internally controlling its own completion (and thus advancement of the sequence), the sequence is inverted so the advancement control is through an external iterator, and each step in the iterable sequence just responds to the next(..) iterator control.

We’ll explore all of these different variations as we go throughout the rest of this appendix, so don’t worry if we ran over those bits far too quickly just now.

The takeaway is that sequences are a more powerful and sensible abstraction for complex asynchrony than just Promises (Promise chains) or just generators, and asynquence is designed to express that abstraction with just the right level of sugar to make async programming more understandable and more enjoyable.

Errors

One important difference with asynquence compared to Promises is with error handling.

With Promises, each individual Promise (step) in a chain can have its own independent error, and each subsequent step has the ability to handle the error (or not). The main reason for this semantic comes (again) from the focus on individual Promises rather than on the chain (sequence) as a whole.

I believe that most of the time, an error in one part of a sequence is generally not recoverable, so the subsequent steps in the sequence are moot and should be skipped. So, by default, an error at any step of a sequence throws the entire sequence into error mode, and the rest of the normal steps are ignored.

If you do need to have a step where its error is recoverable, there are several different API methods that can accommodate, such as try(..) (previously mentioned as a kind of try..catch step) or until(..) (a retry loop that keeps attempting the step until it succeeds or you manually break() the loop). asynquence even has pThen(..) and pCatch(..) methods, which work identically to how normal Promise then(..) and catch(..) work (see Chapter 3), so you can do localized mid-sequence error handling if you so choose.

The point is, you have both options, but the more common one in my experience is the default. With Promises, to get a chain of steps to ignore all steps once an error occurs, you have to take care not to register a rejection handler at any step; otherwise, that error gets swallowed as handled, and the sequence may continue (perhaps unexpectedly). This kind of desired behavior is a bit awkward to properly and reliably handle.

To register a sequence error notification handler, asynquence provides an or(..) sequence method, which also has an alias of onerror(..). You can call this method anywhere in the sequence, and you can register as many handlers as you’d like. That makes it easy for multiple different consumers to listen in on a sequence to know if it failed or not; it’s kind of like an error event handler in that respect.

Just like with Promises, all JS exceptions become sequence errors, or you can programmatically signal a sequence error:

var sq = ASQ( function(done){
    setTimeout( function(){
        // signal an error for the sequence
        done.fail( "Oops" );
    }, 100 );
} )
.then( function(done){
    // will never get here
} )
.or( function(err){
    console.log( err );         // Oops
} )
.then( function(done){
    // won't get here either
} );

// later

sq.or( function(err){
    console.log( err );         // Oops
} );

Another really important difference with error handling in asynquence compared to native Promises is the default behavior of unhandled exceptions. As we discussed at length in Chapter 3, a rejected Promise without a registered rejection handler will just silently hold (aka swallow) the error; you have to remember to always end a chain with a final catch(..).

In asynquence, the assumption is reversed.

If an error occurs on a sequence, and it at that moment has no error handlers registered, the error is reported to the console. In other words, unhandled rejections are by default always reported so as not to be swallowed and missed.

As soon as you register an error handler against a sequence, it opts that sequence out of such reporting, to prevent duplicate noise.

There may, in fact, be cases where you want to create a sequence that may go into the error state before you have a chance to register the handler. This isn’t common, but it can happen from time to time.

In those cases, you can also opt a sequence instance out of error reporting by calling defer() on the sequence. You should only opt out of error reporting if you are sure that you’re going to eventually handle such errors:

var sq1 = ASQ( function(done){
    doesnt.Exist();         // will throw exception to console
} );

var sq2 = ASQ( function(done){
    doesnt.Exist();         // will throw only a sequence error
} )
// opt-out of error reporting
.defer();

setTimeout( function(){
    sq1.or( function(err){
        console.log( err ); // ReferenceError
    } );

    sq2.or( function(err){
        console.log( err ); // ReferenceError
    } );
}, 100 );

// ReferenceError (from sq1)

This is better error handling behavior than Promises themselves have, because it’s the pit of success, not the pit of failure (see Chapter 3).

Note

If a sequence is piped into (aka subsumed by) another sequence—see “Combining Sequences” for a complete description—then the source sequence is opted out of error reporting, but now the target sequence’s error reporting or lack thereof must be considered.

Message Passing

The core principle in CSP is that all communication/interaction between otherwise independent processes must be through formal message passing. Perhaps counter to your expectations, CSP message passing is described as a synchronous action, where the sender process and the receiver process have to mutually be ready for the message to be passed.

How could such synchronous messaging possibly be related to asynchronous programming in JavaScript?

The concreteness of relationship comes from the nature of how ES6 generators are used to produce synchronous-looking actions that under the covers can indeed either be synchronous or (more likely) asynchronous.

In other words, two or more concurrently running generators can appear to synchronously message each other while preserving the fundamental asynchrony of the system because each generator’s code is paused (blocked), waiting on resumption of an asynchronous action.

How does this work?

Imagine a generator (“process”) called “A” that wants to send a message to generator “B.” First, “A” yields the message (thus pausing “A”) to be sent to “B.” When “B” is ready and takes the message, “A” is then resumed (unblocked).

Symmetrically, imagine a generator “A” that wants a message from “B.” “A” yields its request (thus pausing “A”) for the message from “B,” and once “B” sends a message, “A” takes the message and is resumed.

One of the more popular expressions of this CSP message passing theory comes from ClojureScript’s core.async library, and also from the go language. These takes on CSP embody the described communication semantics in a conduit that is opened between processes called a channel.

Note

The term channel is used in part because there are modes in which more than one value can be sent at once into the buffer of the channel; this is similar to what you may think of as a stream. We won’t go into depth about it here, but it can be a very powerful technique for managing streams of data.

In the simplest notion of CSP, a channel that we create between “A” and “B” would have a method called take(..) for blocking to receive a value, and a method called put(..) for blocking to send a value.

This might look like:

var ch = channel();

function *foo() {
    var msg = yield take( ch );

    console.log( msg );
}

function *bar() {
    yield put( ch, "Hello World" );

    console.log( "message sent" );
}

run( foo );
run( bar );
// Hello World
// "message sent"

Compare this structured, synchronous(-looking) message passing interaction to the informal and unstructured message sharing that ASQ#runner(..) provides through the token.messages array and cooperative yielding. In essence, yield put(..) is a single operation that both sends the value and pauses execution to transfer control, whereas in earlier examples we did those as separate steps.

Moreover, CSP stresses that you don’t really explicitly transfer control, but rather design your concurrent routines to block expecting either a value received from the channel, or to block expecting to try to send a message on the channel. The blocking around receiving or sending messages is how you coordinate sequencing of behavior between the coroutines.

Note

Fair warning: this pattern is very powerful but it’s also a little mind twisting to get used to at first. You will want to practice this a bit to get used to this new way of thinking about coordinating your concurrency.

There are several great libraries that have implemented this flavor of CSP in JavaScript, most notably js-csp, which James Long forked and has written extensively about. Also, it cannot be stressed enough how amazing the many writings of David Nolen are on the topic of adapting ClojureScript’s go-style core.async CSP into JS generators.